IV

Adams had a restless morning, and toward noon he asked Miss Perry to call his daughter; he wished to say something to her.

“I thought I heard her leaving the house a couple of hours ago—maybe longer,” the nurse told him. “I’ll go see.” And she returned from the brief errand, her impression confirmed by information from Mrs. Adams. “Yes. She went up to Miss Mildred Palmer’s to see what she’s going to wear to-night.”

Adams looked at Miss Perry wearily, but remained passive, making no inquiries; for he was long accustomed to what seemed to him a kind of jargon among ladies, which became the more incomprehensible when they tried to explain it. A man’s best course, he had found, was just to let it go as so much sound. His sorrowful eyes followed the nurse as she went back to her rocking-chair by the window, and her placidity showed him that there was no mystery for her in the fact that Alice walked two miles to ask so simple a question when there was a telephone in the house. Obviously Miss Perry also comprehended why Alice thought it important to know what Mildred meant to wear. Adams understood why Alice should be concerned with what she herself wore “to look neat and tidy and at her best, why, of course she’d want to,” he thought—but he realized that it was forever beyond him to understand why the clothing of other people had long since become an absorbing part of her life.

Her excursion this morning was no novelty; she was continually going to see what Mildred meant to wear, or what some other girl meant to wear; and when Alice came home from wherever other girls or women had been gathered, she always hurried to her mother with earnest descriptions of the clothing she had seen. At such times, if Adams was present, he might recognize “organdie,” or “taffeta,” or “chiffon,” as words defining certain textiles, but the rest was too technical for him, and he was like a dismal boy at a sermon, just waiting for it to get itself finished. Not the least of the mystery was his wife’s interest: she was almost indifferent about her own clothes, and when she consulted Alice about them spoke hurriedly and with an air of apology; but when Alice described other people’s clothes, Mrs. Adams listened as eagerly as the daughter talked.

“There they go!” he muttered to-day, a moment after he heard the front door closing, a sound recognizable throughout most of the thinly built house. Alice had just returned, and Mrs. Adams called to her from the upper hallway, not far from Adams’s door.

“What did she say?”

“She was sort of snippy about it,” Alice returned, ascending the stairs. “She gets that way sometimes, and pretended she hadn’t made up her mind, but I’m pretty sure it’ll be the maize Georgette with Malines flounces.”

“Didn’t you say she wore that at the Pattersons’?” Mrs. Adams inquired, as Alice arrived at the top of the stairs. “And didn’t you tell me she wore it again at the—”

“Certainly not,” Alice interrupted, rather petulantly. “She’s never worn it but once, and of course she wouldn’t want to wear anything to-night that people have seen her in a lot.”

Miss Perry opened the door of Adams’s room and stepped out. “Your father wants to know if you’ll come and see him a minute, Miss Adams.”

“Poor old thing! Of course!” Alice exclaimed, and went quickly into the room, Miss Perry remaining outside. “What’s the matter, papa? Getting awful sick of lying on his tired old back, I expect.”

“I’ve had kind of a poor morning,” Adams said, as she patted his hand comfortingly. “I been thinking—”

“Didn’t I tell you not to?” she cried, gaily. “Of course you’ll have poor times when you go and do just exactly what I say you mustn’t. You stop thinking this very minute!”

He smiled ruefully, closing his eyes; was silent for a moment, then asked her to sit beside the bed. “I been thinking of something I wanted to say,” he added.

“What like, papa?”

“Well, it’s nothing—much,” he said, with something deprecatory in his tone, as if he felt vague impulses toward both humour and apology. “I just thought maybe I ought to’ve said more to you some time or other about—well, about the way things are, down at Lamb and Company’s, for instance.”

“Now, papa!” She leaned forward in the chair she had taken, and pretended to slap his hand crossly. “Isn’t that exactly what I said you couldn’t think one single think about till you get all well?”

“Well—” he said, and went on slowly, not looking at her, but at the ceiling. “I just thought maybe it wouldn’t been any harm if some time or other I told you something about the way they sort of depend on me down there.”

“Why don’t they show it, then?” she asked, quickly. “That’s just what mama and I have been feeling so much; they don’t appreciate you.”

“Why, yes, they do,” he said. “Yes, they do. They began h’isting my salary the second year I went in there, and they’ve h’isted it a little every two years all the time I’ve worked for ‘em. I’ve been head of the sundries department for seven years now, and I could hardly have more authority in that department unless I was a member of the firm itself.”

“Well, why don’t they make you a member of the firm? That’s what they ought to’ve done! Yes, and long ago!”

Adams laughed, but sighed with more heartiness than he had laughed. “They call me their ‘oldest stand-by’ down there.” He laughed again, apologetically, as if to excuse himself for taking a little pride in this title. “Yes, sir; they say I’m their ‘oldest stand-by’; and I guess they know they can count on my department’s turning in as good a report as they look for, at the end of every month; but they don’t have to take a man into the firm to get him to do my work, dearie.”

“But you said they depended on you, papa.”

“So they do; but of course not so’s they couldn’t get along without me.” He paused, reflecting. “I don’t just seem to know how to put it—I mean how to put what I started out to say. I kind of wanted to tell you—well, it seems funny to me, these last few years, the way your mother’s taken to feeling about it. I’d like to see a better established wholesale drug business than Lamb and Company this side the Alleghanies—I don’t say bigger, I say better established—and it’s kind of funny for a man that’s been with a business like that as long as I have to hear it called a ‘hole.’ It’s kind of funny when you think, yourself, you’ve done pretty fairly well in a business like that, and the men at the head of it seem to think so, too, and put your salary just about as high as anybody could consider customary—well, what I mean, Alice, it’s kind of funny to have your mother think it’s mostly just—mostly just a failure, so to speak.”

His voice had become tremulous in spite of him; and this sign of weakness and emotion had sufficient effect upon Alice. She bent over him suddenly, with her arm about him and her cheek against his. “Poor papa!” she murmured. “Poor papa!”

“No, no,” he said. “I didn’t mean anything to trouble you. I just thought—” He hesitated. “I just wondered—I thought maybe it wouldn’t be any harm if I said something about how things are down there. I got to thinking maybe you didn’t understand it’s a pretty good place. They’re fine people to work for; and they’ve always seemed to think something of me;—the way they took Walter on, for instance, soon as I asked ‘em, last year. Don’t you think that looked a good deal as if they thought something of me, Alice?”

“Yes, papa,” she said, not moving.

“And the work’s right pleasant,” he went on. “Mighty nice boys in our department, Alice. Well, they are in all the departments, for that matter. We have a good deal of fun down there some days.”

She lifted her head. “More than you do at home ‘some days,’ I expect, papa!” she said.

He protested feebly. “Now, I didn’t mean that—I didn’t want to trouble you—”

She looked at him through winking eyelashes. “I’m sorry I called it a ‘hole,’ papa.”

“No, no,” he protested, gently. “It was your mother said that.”

“No. I did, too.”

“Well, if you did, it was only because you’d heard her.”

She shook her head, then kissed him. “I’m going to talk to her,” she said, and rose decisively.

But at this, her father’s troubled voice became quickly louder: “You better let her alone. I just wanted to have a little talk with you. I didn’t mean to start any—your mother won’t—”

“Now, papa!” Alice spoke cheerfully again, and smiled upon him. “I want you to quit worrying! Everything’s going to be all right and nobody’s going to bother you any more about anything. You’ll see!”

She carried her smile out into the hall, but after she had closed the door her face was all pity; and her mother, waiting for her in the opposite room, spoke sympathetically.

“What’s the matter, Alice? What did he say that’s upset you?”

“Wait a minute, mama.” Alice found a handkerchief, used it for eyes and suffused nose, gulped, then suddenly and desolately sat upon the bed. “Poor, poor, poor papa!” she whispered.

“Why?” Mrs. Adams inquired, mildly. “What’s the matter with him? Sometimes you act as if he weren’t getting well. What’s he been talking about?”

“Mama—well, I think I’m pretty selfish. Oh, I do!”

“Did he say you were?”

“Papa? No, indeed! What I mean is, maybe we’re both a little selfish to try to make him go out and hunt around for something new.”

Mrs. Adams looked thoughtful. “Oh, that’s what he was up to!”

“Mama, I think we ought to give it up. I didn’t dream it had really hurt him.”

“Well, doesn’t he hurt us?”

“Never that I know of, mama.”

“I don’t mean by saying things,” Mrs. Adams explained, impatiently. “There are more ways than that of hurting people. When a man sticks to a salary that doesn’t provide for his family, isn’t that hurting them?”

“Oh, it ‘provides’ for us well enough, mama. We have what we need—if I weren’t so extravagant. Oh, I know I am!”

But at this admission her mother cried out sharply. “‘Extravagant!’ You haven’t one tenth of what the other girls you go with have. And you can’t have what you ought to as long as he doesn’t get out of that horrible place. It provides bare food and shelter for us, but what’s that?”

“I don’t think we ought to try any more to change him.”

“You don’t?” Mrs. Adams came and stood before her. “Listen, Alice: your father’s asleep; that’s his trouble, and he’s got to be waked up. He doesn’t know that things have changed. When you and Walter were little children we did have enough—at least it seemed to be about as much as most of the people we knew. But the town isn’t what it was in those days, and times aren’t what they were then, and these fearful prices aren’t the old prices. Everything else but your father has changed, and all the time he’s stood still. He doesn’t know it; he thinks because they’ve given him a hundred dollars more every two years he’s quite a prosperous man! And he thinks that because his children cost him more than he and I cost our parents he gives them—enough!”

“But Walter—” Alice faltered. “Walter doesn’t cost him anything at all any more.” And she concluded, in a stricken voice, “It’s all—me!”

“Why shouldn’t it be?” her mother cried. “You’re young—you’re just at the time when your life should be fullest of good things and happiness. Yet what do you get?”

Alice’s lip quivered; she was not unsusceptible to such an appeal, but she contrived the semblance of a protest. “I don’t have such a bad time not a good deal of the time, anyhow. I’ve got a good many of the things other girls have—”

“You have?” Mrs. Adams was piteously satirical. “I suppose you’ve got a limousine to go to that dance to-night? I suppose you’ve only got to call a florist and tell him to send you some orchids? I suppose you’ve—”

But Alice interrupted this list. Apparently in a single instant all emotion left her, and she became businesslike, as one in the midst of trifles reminded of really serious matters. She got up from the bed and went to the door of the closet where she kept her dresses. “Oh, see here,” she said, briskly. “I’ve decided to wear my white organdie if you could put in a new lining for me. I’m afraid it’ll take you nearly all afternoon.”

She brought forth the dress, displayed it upon the bed, and Mrs. Adams examined it attentively.

“Do you think you could get it done, mama?”

“I don’t see why not,” Mrs. Adams answered, passing a thoughtful hand over the fabric. “It oughtn’t to take more than four or five hours.”

“It’s a shame to have you sit at the machine that long,” Alice said, absently, adding, “And I’m sure we ought to let papa alone. Let’s just give it up, mama.”

Mrs. Adams continued her thoughtful examination of the dress. “Did you buy the chiffon and ribbon, Alice?”

“Yes. I’m sure we oughtn’t to talk to him about it any more, mama.”

“Well, we’ll see.”

“Let’s both agree that we’ll never say another single word to him about it,” said Alice. “It’ll be a great deal better if we just let him make up his mind for himself.”

IX

On a morning, a week after this collapse of festal hopes, Mrs. Adams and her daughter were concluding a three-days’ disturbance, the “Spring housecleaning”—postponed until now by Adams’s long illness—and Alice, on her knees before a chest of drawers, in her mother’s room, paused thoughtfully after dusting a packet of letters wrapped in worn muslin. She called to her mother, who was scrubbing the floor of the hallway just beyond the open door,

“These old letters you had in the bottom drawer, weren’t they some papa wrote you before you were married?”

Mrs. Adams laughed and said, “Yes. Just put ’em back where they were—or else up in the attic—anywhere you want to.”

“Do you mind if I read one, mama?”

Mrs. Adams laughed again. “Oh, I guess you can if you want to. I expect they’re pretty funny!”

Alice laughed in response, and chose the topmost letter of the packet. “My dear, beautiful girl,” it began; and she stared at these singular words. They gave her a shock like that caused by overhearing some bewildering impropriety; and, having read them over to herself several times, she went on to experience other shocks.

My Dear, Beautiful Girl:

This time yesterday I had a mighty bad case of blues because I had not had a word from you in two whole long days and when I do not hear from you every day things look mighty down in the mouth to me. Now it is all so different because your letter has arrived and besides I have got a piece of news I believe you will think as fine as I do. Darling, you will be surprised, so get ready to hear about a big effect on our future. It is this way. I had sort of a suspicion the head of the firm kind of took a fancy to me from the first when I went in there, and liked the way I attended to my work and so when he took me on this business trip with him I felt pretty sure of it and now it turns out I was about right. In return I guess I have got about the best boss in this world and I believe you will think so too. Yes, sweetheart, after the talk I have just had with him if J. A. Lamb asked me to cut my hand off for him I guess I would come pretty near doing it because what he says means the end of our waiting to be together. From New Years on he is going to put me in entire charge of the sundries dept. and what do you think is going to be my salary? Eleven hundred cool dollars a year ($1,100.00). That’s all! Just only a cool eleven hundred per annum! Well, I guess that will show your mother whether I can take care of you or not. And oh how I would like to see your dear, beautiful, loving face when you get this news.

I would like to go out on the public streets and just dance and shout and it is all I can do to help doing it, especially when I know we will be talking it all over together this time next week, and oh my darling, now that your folks have no excuse for putting it off any longer we might be in our own little home before Xmas.

Would you be glad?

Well, darling, this settles everything and makes our future just about as smooth for us as anybody could ask. I can hardly realize after all this waiting life’s troubles are over for you and me and we have nothing to do but to enjoy the happiness granted us by this wonderful, beautiful thing we call life. I know I am not any poet and the one I tried to write about you the day of the picnic was fearful but the way I think about you is a poem.

Write me what you think of the news. I know but write me anyhow.

I’ll get it before we start home and I can be reading it over all the time on the tram.

Your always loving

Virgil.

The sound of her mother’s diligent scrubbing in the hall came back slowly to Alice’s hearing, as she restored the letter to the packet, wrapped the packet in its muslin covering, and returned it to the drawer. She had remained upon her knees while she read the letter; now she sank backward, sitting upon the floor with her hands behind her, an unconscious relaxing for better ease to think. Upon her face there had fallen a look of wonder.

For the first time she was vaguely perceiving that life is everlasting movement. Youth really believes what is running water to be a permanent crystallization and sees time fixed to a point: some people have dark hair, some people have blond hair, some people have gray hair. Until this moment, Alice had no conviction that there was a universe before she came into it. She had always thought of it as the background of herself: the moon was something to make her prettier on a summer night.

But this old letter, through which she saw still flickering an ancient starlight of young love, astounded her. Faintly before her it revealed the whole lives of her father and mother, who had been young, after all—they really had—and their youth was now so utterly passed from them that the picture of it, in the letter, was like a burlesque of them. And so she, herself, must pass to such changes, too, and all that now seemed vital to her would be nothing.

When her work was finished, that afternoon, she went into her father’s room. His recovery had progressed well enough to permit the departure of Miss Perry; and Adams, wearing one of Mrs. Adams’s wrappers over his nightgown, sat in a high-backed chair by a closed window. The weather was warm, but the closed window and the flannel wrapper had not sufficed him: round his shoulders he had an old crocheted scarf of Alice’s; his legs were wrapped in a heavy comfort; and, with these swathings about him, and his eyes closed, his thin and grizzled head making but a slight indentation in the pillow supporting it, he looked old and little and queer.

Alice would have gone out softly, but without opening his eyes, he spoke to her: “Don’t go, dearie. Come sit with the old man a little while.”

She brought a chair near his. “I thought you were napping.”

“No. I don’t hardly ever do that. I just drift a little sometimes.”

“How do you mean you drift, papa?”

He looked at her vaguely. “Oh, I don’t know. Kind of pictures. They get a little mixed up—old times with times still ahead, like planning what to do, you know. That’s as near a nap as I get—when the pictures mix up some. I suppose it’s sort of drowsing.”

She took one of his hands and stroked it. “What do you mean when you say you have pictures like ‘planning what to do’?” she asked.

“I mean planning what to do when I get out and able to go to work again.”

“But that doesn’t need any planning,” Alice said, quickly. “You’re going back to your old place at Lamb’s, of course.”

Adams closed his eyes again, sighing heavily, but made no other response.

“Why, of course you are!” she cried. “What are you talking about?”

His head turned slowly toward her, revealing the eyes, open in a haggard stare. “I heard you the other night when you came from the party,” he said. “I know what was the matter.”

“Indeed, you don’t,” she assured him. “You don’t know anything about it, because there wasn’t anything the matter at all.”

“Don’t you suppose I heard you crying? What’d you cry for if there wasn’t anything the matter?”

“Just nerves, papa. It wasn’t anything else in the world.”

“Never mind,” he said. “Your mother told me.”

“She promised me not to!”

At that Adams laughed mournfully. “It wouldn’t be very likely I’d hear you so upset and not ask about it, even if she didn’t come and tell me on her own hook. You needn’t try to fool me; I tell you I know what was the matter.”

“The only matter was I had a silly fit,” Alice protested. “It did me good, too.”

“How’s that?”

“Because I’ve decided to do something about it, papa.”

“That isn’t the way your mother looks at it,” Adams said, ruefully. “She thinks it’s our place to do something about it. Well, I don’t know—I don’t know; everything seems so changed these days. You’ve always been a good daughter, Alice, and you ought to have as much as any of these girls you go with; she’s convinced me she’s right about that. The trouble is—” He faltered, apologetically, then went on, “I mean the question is—how to get it for you.”

“No!” she cried. “I had no business to make such a fuss just because a lot of idiots didn’t break their necks to get dances with me and because I got mortified about Walter—Walter was pretty terrible—”

“Oh, me, my!” Adams lamented. “I guess that’s something we just have to leave work out itself. What you going to do with a boy nineteen or twenty years old that makes his own living? Can’t whip him. Can’t keep him locked up in the house. Just got to hope he’ll learn better, I suppose.”

“Of course he didn’t want to go to the Palmers’,” Alice explained, tolerantly—“and as mama and I made him take me, and he thought that was pretty selfish in me, why, he felt he had a right to amuse himself any way he could. Of course it was awful that this—that this Mr. Russell should—” In spite of her, the recollection choked her.

“Yes, it was awful,” Adams agreed. “Just awful. Oh, me, my!”

But Alice recovered herself at once, and showed him a cheerful face. “Well, just a few years from now I probably won’t even remember it! I believe hardly anything amounts to as much as we think it does at the time.”

“Well—sometimes it don’t.”

“What I’ve been thinking, papa: it seems to me I ought to do something.”

“What like?”

She looked dreamy, but was obviously serious as she told him: “Well, I mean I ought to be something besides just a kind of nobody. I ought to—” She paused.

“What, dearie?”

“Well—there’s one thing I’d like to do. I’m sure I could do it, too.”

“What?”

“I want to go on the stage: I know I could act.” At this, her father abruptly gave utterance to a feeble cackling of laughter; and when Alice, surprised and a little offended, pressed him for his reason, he tried to evade, saying, “Nothing, dearie. I just thought of something.” But she persisted until he had to explain.

“It made me think of your mother’s sister, your Aunt Flora, that died when you were little,” he said. “She was always telling how she was going on the stage, and talking about how she was certain she’d make a great actress, and all so on; and one day your mother broke out and said she ought ’a’ gone on the stage, herself, because she always knew she had the talent for it—and, well, they got into kind of a spat about which one’d make the best actress. I had to go out in the hall to laugh!”

“Maybe you were wrong,” Alice said, gravely. “If they both felt it, why wouldn’t that look as if there was talent in the family? I’ve always thought—”

“No, dearie,” he said, with a final chuckle. “Your mother and Flora weren’t different from a good many others. I expect ninety percent of all the women I ever knew were just sure they’d be mighty fine actresses if they ever got the chance. Well, I guess it’s a good thing; they enjoy thinking about it and it don’t do anybody any harm.”

Alice was piqued. For several days she had thought almost continuously of a career to be won by her own genius. Not that she planned details, or concerned herself with first steps; her picturings overleaped all that. Principally, she saw her name great on all the billboards of that unkind city, and herself, unchanged in age but glamorous with fame and Paris clothes, returning in a private car. No doubt the pleasantest development of her vision was a dialogue with Mildred; and this became so real that, as she projected it, Alice assumed the proper expressions for both parties to it, formed words with her lips, and even spoke some of them aloud. “No, I haven’t forgotten you, Mrs. Russell. I remember you quite pleasantly, in fact. You were a Miss Palmer, I recall, in those funny old days. Very kind of you, I’m shaw. I appreciate your eagerness to do something for me in your own little home. As you say, a reception would renew my acquaintanceship with many old friends—but I’m shaw you won’t mind my mentioning that I don’t find much inspiration in these provincials. I really must ask you not to press me. An artist’s time is not her own, though of course I could hardly expect you to understand—”

Thus Alice illuminated the dull time; but she retired from the interview with her father still manfully displaying an outward cheerfulness, while depression grew heavier within, as if she had eaten soggy cake. Her father knew nothing whatever of the stage, and she was aware of his ignorance, yet for some reason his innocently skeptical amusement reduced her bright project almost to nothing. Something like this always happened, it seemed; she was continually making these illuminations, all gay with gildings and colourings; and then as soon as anybody else so much as glanced at them—even her father, who loved her—the pretty designs were stricken with a desolating pallor. “Is this life?” Alice wondered, not doubting that the question was original and all her own. “Is it life to spend your time imagining things that aren’t so, and never will be? Beautiful things happen to other people; why should I be the only one they never can happen to?”

The mood lasted overnight; and was still upon her the next afternoon when an errand for her father took her downtown. Adams had decided to begin smoking again, and Alice felt rather degraded, as well as embarrassed, when she went into the large shop her father had named, and asked for the cheap tobacco he used in his pipe. She fell back upon an air of amused indulgence, hoping thus to suggest that her purchase was made for some faithful old retainer, now infirm; and although the calmness of the clerk who served her called for no such elaboration of her sketch, she ornamented it with a little laugh and with the remark, as she dropped the package into her coat-pocket, “I’m sure it’ll please him; they tell me it’s the kind he likes.”

Still playing Lady Bountiful, smiling to herself in anticipation of the joy she was bringing to the simple old negro or Irish follower of the family, she left the shop; but as she came out upon the crowded pavement her smile vanished quickly.

Next to the door of the tobacco-shop, there was the open entrance to a stairway, and, above this rather bleak and dark aperture, a signboard displayed in begrimed gilt letters the information that Frincke’s Business College occupied the upper floors of the building. Furthermore, Frincke here publicly offered “personal instruction and training in practical mathematics, bookkeeping, and all branches of the business life, including stenography, typewriting, etc.”

Alice halted for a moment, frowning at this signboard as though it were something surprising and distasteful which she had never seen before. Yet it was conspicuous in a busy quarter; she almost always passed it when she came downtown, and never without noticing it. Nor was this the first time she had paused to lift toward it that same glance of vague misgiving.

The building was not what the changeful city defined as a modern one, and the dusty wooden stairway, as seen from the pavement, disappeared upward into a smoky darkness. So would the footsteps of a girl ascending there lead to a hideous obscurity, Alice thought; an obscurity as dreary and as permanent as death. And like dry leaves falling about her she saw her wintry imaginings in the May air: pretty girls turning into withered creatures as they worked at typing-machines; old maids “taking dictation” from men with double chins; Alice saw old maids of a dozen different kinds “taking dictation.” Her mind’s eye was crowded with them, as it always was when she passed that stairway entrance; and though they were all different from one another, all of them looked a little like herself.

She hated the place, and yet she seldom hurried by it or averted her eyes. It had an unpleasant fascination for her, and a mysterious reproach, which she did not seek to fathom. She walked on thoughtfully today; and when, at the next corner, she turned into the street that led toward home, she was given a surprise. Arthur Russell came rapidly from behind her, lifting his hat as she saw him.

“Are you walking north, Miss Adams?” he asked. “Do you mind if I walk with you?”

She was not delighted, but seemed so. “How charming!” she cried, giving him a little flourish of the shapely hands; and then, because she wondered if he had seen her coming out of the tobacco-shop, she laughed and added, “I’ve just been on the most ridiculous errand!”

“What was that?”

“To order some cigars for my father. He’s been quite ill, poor man, and he’s so particular—but what in the world do I know about cigars?”

Russell laughed. “Well, what do you know about ’em? Did you select by the price?”

“Mercy, no!” she exclaimed, and added, with an afterthought, “Of course he wrote down the name of the kind he wanted and I gave it to the shopman. I could never have pronounced it.”

X

In her pocket as she spoke her hand rested upon the little sack of tobacco, which responded accusingly to the touch of her restless fingers; and she found time to wonder why she was building up this fiction for Mr. Arthur Russell. His discovery of Walter’s device for whiling away the dull evening had shamed and distressed her; but she would have suffered no less if almost any other had been the discoverer. In this gentleman, after hearing that he was Mildred’s Mr. Arthur Russell, Alice felt not the slightest “personal interest”; and there was yet to develop in her life such a thing as an interest not personal. At twenty-two this state of affairs is not unique.

So far as Alice was concerned Russell might have worn a placard, “Engaged.” She looked upon him as diners entering a restaurant look upon tables marked “Reserved”: the glance, slightly discontented, passes on at once. Or so the eye of a prospector wanders querulously over staked and established claims on the mountainside, and seeks the virgin land beyond; unless, indeed, the prospector be dishonest. But Alice was no claim-jumper—so long as the notice of ownership was plainly posted.

Though she was indifferent now, habit ruled her: and, at the very time she wondered why she created fictitious cigars for her father, she was also regretting that she had not boldly carried her Malacca stick downtown with her. Her vivacity increased automatically.

“Perhaps the clerk thought you wanted the cigars for yourself,” Russell suggested. “He may have taken you for a Spanish countess.”

“I’m sure he did!” Alice agreed, gaily; and she hummed a bar or two of “LaPaloma,” snapping her fingers as castanets, and swaying her body a little, to suggest the accepted stencil of a “Spanish Dancer.” “Would you have taken me for one, Mr. Russell?” she asked, as she concluded the impersonation.

“I? Why, yes,” he said. “I’d take you for anything you wanted me to.”

“Why, what a speech!” she cried, and, laughing, gave him a quick glance in which there glimmered some real surprise. He was looking at her quizzically, but with the liveliest appreciation. Her surprise increased; and she was glad that he had joined her.

To be seen walking with such a companion added to her pleasure. She would have described him as “altogether quite stunning-looking”; and she liked his tall, dark thinness, his gray clothes, his soft hat, and his clean brown shoes; she liked his easy swing of the stick he carried.

“Shouldn’t I have said it?” he asked. “Would you rather not be taken for a Spanish countess?”

“That isn’t it,” she explained. “You said—”

“I said I’d take you for whatever you wanted me to. Isn’t that all right?”

“It would all depend, wouldn’t it?”

“Of course it would depend on what you wanted.”

“Oh, no!” she laughed. “It might depend on a lot of things.”

“Such as?”

“Well—” She hesitated, having the mischievous impulse to say, “Such as Mildred!” But she decided to omit this reference, and became serious, remembering Russell’s service to her at Mildred’s house. “Speaking of what I want to be taken for,” she said;—“I’ve been wondering ever since the other night what you did take me for! You must have taken me for the sister of a professional gambler, I’m afraid!”

Russell’s look of kindness was the truth about him, she was to discover; and he reassured her now by the promptness of his friendly chuckle. “Then your young brother told you where I found him, did he? I kept my face straight at the time, but I laughed afterward—to myself. It struck me as original, to say the least: his amusing himself with those darkies.”

“Walter is original,” Alice said; and, having adopted this new view of her brother’s eccentricities, she impulsively went on to make it more plausible. “He’s a very odd boy, and I was afraid you’d misunderstand. He tells wonderful ‘darky stories,’ and he’ll do anything to draw coloured people out and make them talk; and that’s what he was doing at Mildred’s when you found him for me—he says he wins their confidence by playing dice with them. In the family we think he’ll probably write about them some day. He’s rather literary.”

“Are you?” Russell asked, smiling.

“I? Oh—” She paused, lifting both hands in a charming gesture of helplessness. “Oh, I’m just—me!”

His glance followed the lightly waved hands with keen approval, then rose to the lively and colourful face, with its hazel eyes, its small and pretty nose, and the lip-caught smile which seemed the climax of her decorative transition. Never had he seen a creature so plastic or so wistful.

Here was a contrast to his cousin Mildred, who was not wistful, and controlled any impulses toward plasticity, if she had them. “By George!” he said. “But you are different!”

With that, there leaped in her such an impulse of roguish gallantry as she could never resist. She turned her head, and, laughing and bright-eyed, looked him full in the face.

“From whom?” she cried.

“From—everybody!” he said. “Are you a mind-reader?”

“Why?”

“How did you know I was thinking you were different from my cousin, Mildred Palmer?”

“What makes you think I did know it?”

“Nonsense!” he said. “You knew what I was thinking and I knew you knew.”

“Yes,” she said with cool humour. “How intimate that seems to make us all at once!”

Russell left no doubt that he was delighted with these gaieties of hers. “By George!” he exclaimed again. “I thought you were this sort of girl the first moment I saw you!”

“What sort of girl? Didn’t Mildred tell you what sort of girl I am when she asked you to dance with me?”

“She didn’t ask me to dance with you—I’d been looking at you. You were talking to some old ladies, and I asked Mildred who you were.”

“Oh, so Mildred didn’t—” Alice checked herself. “Who did she tell you I was?”

“She just said you were a Miss Adams, so I—”

“ ‘A’ Miss Adams?” Alice interrupted.

“Yes. Then I said I’d like to meet you.”

“I see. You thought you’d save me from the old ladies.”

“No. I thought I’d save myself from some of the girls Mildred was getting me to dance with. There was a Miss Dowling—”

“Poor man!” Alice said, gently, and her impulsive thought was that Mildred had taken few chances, and that as a matter of self-defense her carefulness might have been well founded. This Mr. Arthur Russell was a much more responsive person than one had supposed.

“So, Mr. Russell, you don’t know anything about me except what you thought when you first saw me?”

“Yes, I know I was right when I thought it.”

“You haven’t told me what you thought.”

“I thought you were like what you are like.”

“Not very definite, is it? I’m afraid you shed more light a minute or so ago, when you said how different from Mildred you thought I was. That was definite, unfortunately!”

“I didn’t say it,” Russell explained. “I thought it, and you read my mind. That’s the sort of girl I thought you were—one that could read a man’s mind. Why do you say ‘unfortunately’ you’re not like Mildred?”

Alice’s smooth gesture seemed to sketch Mildred. “Because she’s perfect—why, she’s perfectly perfect! She never makes a mistake, and everybody looks up to her—oh, yes, we all fairly adore her! She’s like some big, noble, cold statue—’way above the rest of us—and she hardly ever does anything mean or treacherous. Of all the girls I know I believe she’s played the fewest really petty tricks. She’s—”

Russell interrupted; he looked perplexed. “You say she’s perfectly perfect, but that she does play some—”

Alice laughed, as if at his sweet innocence. “Men are so funny!” she informed him. “Of course girls all do mean things sometimes. My own career’s just one long brazen smirch of ’em! What I mean is, Mildred’s perfectly perfect compared to the rest of us.”

“I see,” he said, and seemed to need a moment or two of thoughtfulness. Then he inquired, “What sort of treacherous things do you do?”

“I? Oh, the very worst kind! Most people bore me particularly the men in this town—and I show it.”

“But I shouldn’t call that treacherous, exactly.”

“Well, they do,” Alice laughed. “It’s made me a terribly unpopular character! I do a lot of things they hate. For instance, at a dance I’d a lot rather find some clever old woman and talk to her than dance with nine-tenths of these nonentities. I usually do it, too.”

“But you danced as if you liked it. You danced better than any other girl I—”

“This flattery of yours doesn’t quite turn my head, Mr. Russell,” Alice interrupted. “Particularly since Mildred only gave you Ella Dowling to compare with me!”

“Oh, no,” he insisted. “There were others—and of course Mildred, herself.”

“Oh, of course, yes. I forgot that. Well—” She paused, then added, “I certainly ought to dance well.”

“Why is it so much a duty?”

“When I think of the dancing-teachers and the expense to papa! All sorts of fancy instructors—I suppose that’s what daughters have fathers for, though, isn’t it? To throw money away on them?”

“You don’t—” Russell began, and his look was one of alarm. “You haven’t taken up—”

She understood his apprehension and responded merrily, “Oh, murder, no! You mean you’re afraid I break out sometimes in a piece of cheesecloth and run around a fountain thirty times, and then, for an encore, show how much like snakes I can make my arms look.”

“I said you were a mind-reader!” he exclaimed. “That’s exactly what I was pretending to be afraid you might do.”

“ ‘Pretending?’ That’s nicer of you. No; it’s not my mania.”

“What is?”

“Oh, nothing in particular that I know of just now. Of course I’ve had the usual one: the one that every girl goes through.”

“What’s that?”

“Good heavens, Mr. Russell, you can’t expect me to believe you’re really a man of the world if you don’t know that every girl has a time in her life when she’s positive she’s divinely talented for the stage! It’s the only universal rule about women that hasn’t got an exception. I don’t mean we all want to go on the stage, but we all think we’d be wonderful if we did. Even Mildred. Oh, she wouldn’t confess it to you: you’d have to know her a great deal better than any man can ever know her to find out.”

“I see,” he said. “Girls are always telling us we can’t know them. I wonder if you—”

She took up his thought before he expressed it, and again he was fascinated by her quickness, which indeed seemed to him almost telepathic. “Oh, but don’t we know one another, though!” she cried.

“Such things we have to keep secret—things that go on right before your eyes!”

“Why don’t some of you tell us?” he asked.

“We can’t tell you.”

“Too much honour?”

“No. Not even too much honour among thieves, Mr. Russell. We don’t tell you about our tricks against one another because we know it wouldn’t make any impression on you. The tricks aren’t played against you, and you have a soft side for cats with lovely manners!”

“What about your tricks against us?”

“Oh, those!” Alice laughed. “We think they’re rather cute!”

“Bravo!” he cried, and hammered the ferrule of his stick upon the pavement.

“What’s the applause for?”

“For you. What you said was like running up the black flag to the masthead.”

“Oh, no. It was just a modest little sign in a pretty flowerbed: ‘Gentlemen, beware!’ ”

“I see I must,” he said, gallantly.

“Thanks! But I mean, beware of the whole bloomin’ garden!” Then, picking up a thread that had almost disappeared: “You needn’t think you’ll ever find out whether I’m right about Mildred’s not being an exception by asking her,” she said. “She won’t tell you: she’s not the sort that ever makes a confession.”

But Russell had not followed her shift to the former topic. “ ‘Mildred’s not being an exception?’ ” he said, vaguely. “I don’t—”

“An exception about thinking she could be a wonderful thing on the stage if she only cared to. If you asked her I’m pretty sure she’d say, ‘What nonsense!’ Mildred’s the dearest, finest thing anywhere, but you won’t find out many things about her by asking her.”

Russell’s expression became more serious, as it did whenever his cousin was made their topic. “You think not?” he said. “You think she’s—”

“No. But it’s not because she isn’t sincere exactly. It’s only because she has such a lot to live up to. She has to live up to being a girl on the grand style to herself, I mean, of course.” And without pausing Alice rippled on, “You ought to have seen me when I had the stage-fever! I used to play ‘Juliet’ all alone in my room.’ She lifted her arms in graceful entreaty, pleading musically,

“O, swear not by the moon, the inconstant moon,
That monthly changes in her circled orb, Lest thy love prove—”

She broke off abruptly with a little flourish, snapping thumb and finger of each outstretched hand, then laughed and said, “Papa used to make such fun of me! Thank heaven, I was only fifteen; I was all over it by the next year.”

“No wonder you had the fever,” Russell observed. “You do it beautifully. Why didn’t you finish the line?”

“Which one? ‘Lest thy love prove likewise variable’? Juliet was saying it to a man, you know. She seems to have been ready to worry about his constancy pretty early in their affair!”

Her companion was again thoughtful. “Yes,” he said, seeming to be rather irksomely impressed with Alice’s suggestion. “Yes; it does appear so.”

Alice glanced at his serious face, and yielded to an audacious temptation. “You mustn’t take it so hard,” she said, flippantly.

“It isn’t about you: it’s only about Romeo and Juliet.”

“See here!” he exclaimed. “You aren’t at your mind-reading again, are you? There are times when it won’t do, you know!”

She leaned toward him a little, as if companionably: they were walking slowly, and this geniality of hers brought her shoulder in light contact with his for a moment. “Do you dislike my mind-reading?” she asked, and, across their two just touching shoulders, gave him her sudden look of smiling wistfulness. “Do you hate it?”

He shook his head. “No, I don’t,” he said, gravely. “It’s quite pleasant. But I think it says, ‘Gentlemen, beware!’ ”

She instantly moved away from him, with the lawless and frank laugh of one who is delighted to be caught in a piece of hypocrisy. “How lovely!” she cried. Then she pointed ahead. “Our walk is nearly over. We’re coming to the foolish little house where I live. It’s a queer little place, but my father’s so attached to it the family have about given up hope of getting him to build a real house farther out. He doesn’t mind our being extravagant about anything else, but he won’t let us alter one single thing about his precious little old house. Well!” She halted, and gave him her hand. “Adieu!”

“I couldn’t,” he began; hesitated, then asked: “I couldn’t come in with you for a little while?”

“Not now,” she said, quickly. “You can come—” She paused.

“When?”

“Almost any time.” She turned and walked slowly up the path, but he waited. “You can come in the evening if you like,” she called back to him over her shoulder.

“Soon?”

“As soon as you like!” She waved her hand; then ran indoors and watched him from a window as he went up the street. He walked rapidly, a fine, easy figure, swinging his stick in a way that suggested exhilaration. Alice, staring after him through the irregular apertures of a lace curtain, showed no similar buoyancy. Upon the instant she closed the door all sparkle left her: she had become at once the simple and sometimes troubled girl her family knew.

“What is going on out there?” her mother asked, approaching from the dining-room.

“Oh, nothing,” Alice said, indifferently, as she turned away. “That Mr. Russell met me downtown and walked up with me.”

“Mr. Russell? Oh, the one that’s engaged to Mildred?”

“Well—I don’t know for certain. He didn’t seem so much like an engaged man to me.” And she added, in the tone of thoughtful preoccupation: “Anyhow—not so terribly!”

Then she ran upstairs, gave her father his tobacco, filled his pipe for him, and petted him as he lighted it.

XI

After that, she went to her room and sat down before her three-leaved mirror. There was where she nearly always sat when she came into her room, if she had nothing in mind to do. She went to that chair as naturally as a dog goes to his corner.

She leaned forward, observing her profile; gravity seemed to be her mood. But after a long, almost motionless scrutiny, she began to produce dramatic sketches upon that ever-ready stage, her countenance: she showed gaiety, satire, doubt, gentleness, appreciation of a companion and love-in-hiding—all studied in profile first, then repeated for a “three-quarter view.” Subsequently she ran through them, facing herself in full.

In this manner she outlined a playful scenario for her next interview with Arthur Russell; but grew solemn again, thinking of the impression she had already sought to give him. She had no twinges for any underminings of her “most intimate friend”—in fact, she felt that her work on a new portrait of Mildred for Mr.

Russell had been honest and accurate. But why had it been her instinct to show him an Alice Adams who didn’t exist?

Almost everything she had said to him was upon spontaneous impulse, springing to her lips on the instant; yet it all seemed to have been founded upon a careful design, as if some hidden self kept such designs in stock and handed them up to her, ready-made, to be used for its own purpose. What appeared to be the desired result was a false-coloured image in Russell’s mind; but if he liked that image he wouldn’t be liking Alice Adams; nor would anything he thought about the image be a thought about her.

Nevertheless, she knew she would go on with her false, fancy colourings of this nothing as soon as she saw him again; she had just been practicing them. “What’s the idea?” she wondered. “What makes me tell such lies? Why shouldn’t I be just myself?” And then she thought, “But which one is myself?”

Her eyes dwelt on the solemn eyes in the mirror; and her lips, disquieted by a deepening wonder, parted to whisper:

“Who in the world are you?”

The apparition before her had obeyed her like an alert slave, but now, as she subsided to a complete stillness, that aspect changed to the old mockery with which mirrors avenge their wrongs. The nucleus of some queer thing seemed to gather and shape itself behind the nothingness of the reflected eyes until it became almost an actual strange presence. If it could be identified, perhaps the presence was that of the hidden designer who handed up the false, ready-made pictures, and, for unknown purposes, made Alice exhibit them; but whatever it was, she suddenly found it monkey-like and terrifying. In a flutter she jumped up and went to another part of the room.

A moment or two later she was whistling softly as she hung her light coat over a wooden triangle in her closet, and her musing now was quainter than the experience that led to it; for what she thought was this, “I certainly am a queer girl!” She took a little pride in so much originality, believing herself probably the only person in the world to have such thoughts as had been hers since she entered the room, and the first to be disturbed by a strange presence in the mirror. In fact, the effect of the tiny episode became apparent in that look of preoccupied complacency to be seen for a time upon any girl who has found reason to suspect that she is a being without counterpart.

This slight glow, still faintly radiant, was observed across the dinner-table by Walter, but he misinterpreted it. “What you lookin’ so self-satisfied about?” he inquired, and added in his knowing way, “I saw you, all right, cutie!”

“Where’d you see me?”

“Downtown.”

“This afternoon, you mean, Walter?”

“Yes, ‘this afternoon, I mean, Walter,’ ” he returned, burlesquing her voice at least happily enough to please himself; for he laughed applausively. “Oh, you never saw me! I passed you close enough to pull a tooth, but you were awful busy. I never did see anybody as busy as you get, Alice, when you’re towin’ a barge. My, but you keep your hands goin’! Looked like the air was full of ’em! That’s why I’m onto why you look so tickled this evening; I saw you with that big fish.”

Mrs. Adams laughed benevolently; she was not displeased with this rallying. “Well, what of it, Walter?” she asked. “If you happen to see your sister on the street when some nice young man is being attentive to her—”

Walter barked and then cackled. “Whoa, Sal!” he said. “You got the parts mixed. It’s little Alice that was ‘being attentive.’ I know the big fish she was attentive to, all right, too.”

“Yes,” his sister retorted, quietly. “I should think you might have recognized him, Walter.”

Walter looked annoyed. “Still harpin’ on that!” he complained. “The kind of women I like, if they get sore they just hit you somewhere on the face and then they’re through. By the way, I heard this Russell was supposed to be your dear, old, sweet friend Mildred’s steady. What you doin’ walkin’ as close to him as all that?”

Mrs. Adams addressed her son in gentle reproof, “Why Walter!”

“Oh, never mind, mama,” Alice said. “To the horrid all things are horrid.”

“Get out!” Walter protested, carelessly. “I heard all about this Russell down at the shop. Young Joe Lamb’s such a talker I wonder he don’t ruin his grandfather’s business; he keeps all us cheap help standin’ round listening to him nine-tenths of our time. Well, Joe told me this Russell’s some kin or other to the Palmer family, and he’s got some little money of his own, and he’s puttin’ it into ole Palmer’s trust company and Palmer’s goin’ to make him a vice-president of the company. Sort of a keep-the-money-in-the-family arrangement, Joe Lamb says.”

Mrs. Adams looked thoughtful. “I don’t see—” she began.

“Why, this Russell’s supposed to be tied up to Mildred,” her son explained. “When ole Palmer dies this Russell will be his son-in-law, and all he’ll haf’ to do’ll be to barely lift his feet and step into the ole man’s shoes. It’s certainly a mighty fat hand-me-out for this Russell! You better lay off o’ there, Alice. Pick somebody that’s got less to lose and you’ll make better showing.”

Mrs. Adams’s air of thoughtfulness had not departed. “But you say this Mr. Russell is well off on his own account, Walter.”

“Oh, Joe Lamb says he’s got some little of his own. Didn’t know how much.”

“Well, then—”

Walter laughed his laugh. “Cut it out,” he bade her. “Alice wouldn’t run in fourth place.”

Alice had been looking at him in a detached way, as though estimating the value of a specimen in a collection not her own. “Yes,” she said, indifferently. “You really are vulgar, Walter.”

He had finished his meal; and, rising, he came round the table to her and patted her good-naturedly on the shoulder. “Good ole Allie!” he said. “honest, you wouldn’t run in fourth place. If I was you I’d never even start in the class. That frozen-face gang will rule you off the track soon as they see your colours.”

“Walter!” his mother said again.

“Well, ain’t I her brother?” he returned, seeming to be entirely serious and direct, for the moment, at least. “I like the ole girl all right. Fact is, sometimes I’m kind of sorry for her.”

“But what’s it all about?” Alice cried. “Simply because you met me downtown with a man I never saw but once before and just barely know! Why all this palaver?”

“ ‘Why?’ ” he repeated, grinning. “Well, I’ve seen you start before, you know!” He went to the door, and paused. “I got no date tonight. Take you to the movies, you care to go.”

She declined crisply. “No, thanks!”

“Come on,” he said, as pleasantly as he knew how.

“Give me a chance to show you a better time than we had up at that frozen-face joint. I’ll get you some chop suey afterward.”

“No, thanks!”

“All right,” he responded and waved a flippant adieu. “As the barber says, ‘The better the advice, the worse it’s wasted!’ Good night!”

Alice shrugged her shoulders; but a moment or two later, as the jar of the carelessly slammed front door went through the house, she shook her head, reconsidering. “Perhaps I ought to have gone with him. It might have kept him away from whatever dreadful people are his friends—at least for one night.”

“Oh, I’m sure Walter’s a good boy,” Mrs. Adams said, soothingly; and this was what she almost always said when either her husband or Alice expressed such misgivings. “He’s odd, and he’s picked up right queer manners; but that’s only because we haven’t given him advantages like the other young men. But I’m sure he’s a good boy.”

She reverted to the subject a little later, while she washed the dishes and Alice wiped them. “Of course Walter could take his place with the other nice boys of the town even yet,” she said. “I mean, if we could afford to help him financially. They all belong to the country clubs and have cars and—”

“Let’s don’t go into that any more, mama,” the daughter begged her. “What’s the use?”

“It could be of use,” Mrs. Adams insisted. “It could if your father—”

“But papa can’t.”

“Yes, he can.”

“But how can he? He told me a man of his age can’t give up a business he’s been in practically all his life, and just go groping about for something that might never turn up at all. I think he’s right about it, too, of course!”

Mrs. Adams splashed among the plates with a new vigour heightened by an old bitterness. “Oh, yes,” she said. “He talks that way; but he knows better.”

“How could he ‘know better,’ mama?”

“He knows how!”

“But what does he know?”

Mrs. Adams tossed her head. “You don’t suppose I’m such a fool I’d be urging him to give up something for nothing, do you, Alice? Do you suppose I’d want him to just go ‘groping around’ like he was telling you? That would be crazy, of course. Little as his work at Lamb’s brings in, I wouldn’t be so silly as to ask him to give it up just on a chance he could find something else. Good gracious, Alice, you must give me credit for a little intelligence once in a while!”

Alice was puzzled. “But what else could there be except a chance? I don’t see—”

“Well, I do,” her mother interrupted, decisively. “That man could make us all well off right now if he wanted to. We could have been rich long ago if he’d ever really felt as he ought to about his family.”

“What! Why, how could—”

“You know how as well as I do,” Mrs. Adams said, crossly. “I guess you haven’t forgotten how he treated me about it the Sunday before he got sick.”

She went on with her work, putting into it a sudden violence inspired by the recollection; but Alice, enlightened, gave utterance to a laugh of lugubrious derision. “Oh, the glue factory again!” she cried. “How silly!” And she renewed her laughter.

So often do the great projects of parents appear ignominious to their children. Mrs. Adams’s conception of a glue factory as a fairy godmother of this family was an absurd old story which Alice had never taken seriously. She remembered that when she was about fifteen her mother began now and then to say something to Adams about a “glue factory,” rather timidly, and as a vague suggestion, but never without irritating him. Then, for years, the preposterous subject had not been mentioned; possibly because of some explosion on the part of Adams, when his daughter had not been present. But during the last year Mrs. Adams had quietly gone back to these old hints, reviving them at intervals and also reviving her husband’s irritation. Alice’s bored impression was that her mother wanted him to found, or buy, or do something, or other, about a glue factory; and that he considered the proposal so impracticable as to be insulting. The parental conversations took place when neither Alice nor Walter was at hand, but sometimes Alice had come in upon the conclusion of one, to find her father in a shouting mood, and shocking the air behind him with profane monosyllables as he departed. Mrs. Adams would be left quiet and troubled; and when Alice, sympathizing with the goaded man, inquired of her mother why these tiresome bickerings had been renewed, she always got the brooding and cryptic answer, “He could do it—if he wanted to.” Alice failed to comprehend the desirability of a glue factory—to her mind a father engaged in a glue factory lacked impressiveness; had no advantage over a father employed by Lamb and Company; and she supposed that Adams knew better than her mother whether such an enterprise would be profitable or not. Emphatically, he thought it would not, for she had heard him shouting at the end of one of these painful interviews, “You can keep up your dang talk till you die and I die, but I’ll never make one God’s cent that way!”

There had been a culmination. Returning from church on the Sunday preceding the collapse with which Adams’s illness had begun, Alice found her mother downstairs, weeping and intimidated, while her father’s stamping footsteps were loudly audible as he strode up and down his room overhead. So were his endless repetitions of invective loudly audible: “That woman! Oh, that woman; Oh, that danged woman!”

Mrs. Adams admitted to her daughter that it was “the old glue factory” and that her husband’s wildness had frightened her into a “solemn promise” never to mention the subject again so long as she had breath. Alice laughed. The “glue factory” idea was not only a bore, but ridiculous, and her mother’s evident seriousness about it one of those inexplicable vagaries we sometimes discover in the people we know best. But this Sunday rampage appeared to be the end of it, and when Adams came down to dinner, an hour later, he was unusually cheerful. Alice was glad he had gone wild enough to settle the glue factory once and for all; and she had ceased to think of the episode long before Friday of that week, when Adams was brought home in the middle of the afternoon by his old employer, the “great J. A. Lamb,” in the latter’s car.

During the long illness the “glue factory” was completely forgotten, by Alice at least; and her laugh was rueful as well as derisive now, in the kitchen, when she realized that her mother’s mind again dwelt upon this abandoned nuisance. “I thought you’d got over all that nonsense, mama,” she said.

Mrs. Adams smiled, pathetically. “Of course you think it’s nonsense, dearie. Young people think everything’s nonsense that they don’t know anything about.”

“Good gracious!” Alice cried. “I should think I used to hear enough about that horrible old glue factory to know something about it!”

“No,” her mother returned patiently. “You’ve never heard anything about it at all.”

“I haven’t?”

“No. Your father and I didn’t discuss it before you children. All you ever heard was when he’d get in such a rage, after we’d been speaking of it, that he couldn’t control himself when you came in. Wasn’t I always quiet? Did I ever go on talking about it?”

“No; perhaps not. But you’re talking about it now, mama, after you promised never to mention it again.”

“I promised not to mention it to your father,” said Mrs. Adams, gently. “I haven’t mentioned it to him, have I?”

“Ah, but if you mention it to me I’m afraid you will mention it to him. You always do speak of things that you have on your mind, and you might get papa all stirred up again about—” Alice paused, a light of divination flickering in her eyes. “Oh!” she cried. “I see!”

“What do you see?”

“You have been at him about it!”

“Not one single word!”

“No!” Alice cried. “Not a word, but that’s what you’ve meant all along! You haven’t spoken the words to him, but all this urging him to change, to ‘find something better to go into’—it’s all been about nothing on earth but your foolish old glue factory that you know upsets him, and you gave your solemn word never to speak to him about again! You didn’t say it, but you meant it—and he knows that’s what you meant! Oh, mama!”

Mrs. Adams, with her hands still automatically at work in the flooded dishpan, turned to face her daughter. “Alice,” she said, tremulously, “what do I ask for myself?”

“What?”

“I say, What do I ask for myself? Do you suppose I want anything? Don’t you know I’d be perfectly content on your father’s present income if I were the only person to be considered? What do I care about any pleasure for myself? I’d be willing never to have a maid again; I don’t mind doing the work. If we didn’t have any children I’d be glad to do your father’s cooking and the housework and the washing and ironing, too, for the rest of my life. I wouldn’t care. I’m a poor cook and a poor housekeeper; I don’t do anything well; but it would be good enough for just him and me. I wouldn’t ever utter one word of com—”

“Oh, goodness!” Alice lamented. “What is it all about?”

“It’s about this,” said Mrs. Adams, swallowing. “You and Walter are a new generation and you ought to have the same as the rest of the new generation get. Poor Walter—asking you to go to the movies and a Chinese restaurant: the best he had to offer! Don’t you suppose I see how the poor boy is deteriorating? Don’t you suppose I know what you have to go through, Alice? And when I think of that man upstairs—” The agitated voice grew louder. “When I think of him and know that nothing in the world but his stubbornness keeps my children from having all they want and what they ought to have, do you suppose I’m going to hold myself bound to keep to the absolute letter of a silly promise he got from me by behaving like a crazy man? I can’t! I can’t do it! No mother could sit by and see him lock up a horn of plenty like that in his closet when the children were starving!”

“Oh, goodness, goodness me!” Alice protested. “We aren’t precisely ‘starving,’ are we?”

Mrs. Adams began to weep. “It’s just the same. Didn’t I see how flushed and pretty you looked, this afternoon, after you’d been walking with this young man that’s come here? Do you suppose he’d look at a girl like Mildred Palmer if you had what you ought to have? Do you suppose he’d be going into business with her father if your father—”

“Good heavens, mama; you’re worse than Walter: I just barely know the man! don’t be so absurd!”

“Yes, I’m always ‘absurd,’ ” Mrs. Adams moaned. “All I can do is cry, while your father sits upstairs, and his horn of plenty—”

But Alice interrupted with a peal of desperate laughter. “Oh, that ‘horn of plenty!’ Do come down to earth, mama. How can you call a glue factory, that doesn’t exist except in your mind, a ‘horn of plenty’? Do let’s be a little rational!”

“It could be a horn of plenty,” the tearful Mrs. Adams insisted. “It could! You don’t understand a thing about it.”

“Well, I’m willing,” Alice said, with tired skepticism. “Make me understand, then. Where’d you ever get the idea?”

Mrs. Adams withdrew her hands from the water, dried them on a towel, and then wiped her eyes with a handkerchief. “Your father could make a fortune if he wanted to,” she said, quietly. “At least, I don’t say a fortune, but anyhow a great deal more than he does make.”

“Yes, I’ve heard that before, mama, and you think he could make it out of a glue factory. What I’m asking is: How?”

“How? Why, by making glue and selling it. Don’t you know how bad most glue is when you try to mend anything? A good glue is one of the rarest things there is; and it would just sell itself, once it got started. Well, your father knows how to make as good a glue as there is in the world.”

Alice was not interested. “What of it? I suppose probably anybody could make it if they wanted to.”

“I said you didn’t know anything about it. Nobody else could make it. Your father knows a formula for making it.”

“What of that?”

“It’s a secret formula. It isn’t even down on paper. It’s worth any amount of money.”

“ ‘Any amount?’ ” Alice said, remaining incredulous. “Why hasn’t papa sold it then?”

“Just because he’s too stubborn to do anything with it at all!”

“How did papa get it?”

“He got it before you were born, just after we were married. I didn’t think much about it then: it wasn’t till you were growing up and I saw how much we needed money that I—”

“Yes, but how did papa get it?” Alice began to feel a little more curious about this possible buried treasure. “Did he invent it?”

“Partly,” Mrs. Adams said, looking somewhat preoccupied. “He and another man invented it.”

“Then maybe the other man—”

“He’s dead.”

“Then his family—”

“I don’t think he left any family,” Mrs. Adams said. “Anyhow, it belongs to your father. At least it belongs to him as much as it does to any one else. He’s got an absolutely perfect right to do anything he wants to with it, and it would make us all comfortable if he’d do what I want him to—and he knows it would, too!”

Alice shook her head pityingly. “Poor mama!” she said. “Of course he knows it wouldn’t do anything of the kind, or else he’d have done it long ago.”

“He would, you say?” her mother cried. “That only shows how little you know him!”

“Poor mama!” Alice said again, soothingly. “If papa were like what you say he is, he’d be—why, he’d be crazy!”

Mrs. Adams agreed with a vehemence near passion. “You’re right about him for once: that’s just what he is! He sits up there in his stubbornness and lets us slave here in the kitchen when if he wanted to—if he’d so much as lift his little finger—”

“Oh, come, now!” Alice laughed. “You can’t build even a glue factory with just one little finger.”

Mrs. Adams seemed about to reply that finding fault with a figure of speech was beside the point; but a ringing of the front door bell forestalled the retort. “Now, who do you suppose that is?” she wondered aloud, then her face brightened. “Ah—did Mr. Russell ask if he could—”

“No, he wouldn’t be coming this evening,” Alice said. “Probably it’s the great J. A. Lamb: he usually stops for a minute on Thursdays to ask how papa’s getting along. I’ll go.”

She tossed her apron off, and as she went through the house her expression was thoughtful. She was thinking vaguely about the glue factory and wondering if there might be “something in it” after all. If her mother was right about the rich possibilities of Adams’s secret—but that was as far as Alice’s speculations upon the matter went at this time: they were checked, partly by the thought that her father probably hadn’t enough money for such an enterprise, and partly by the fact that she had arrived at the front door.

XVIII

That was a thought almost continuously in his mind, even when he was hardest at work; and, as the days went on and he could not free himself, he became querulous about it. ‚ÄúI guess I‚Äôm the biggest dang fool alive,‚Äù he told his wife as they sat together one evening. ‚ÄúI got plenty else to bother me, without worrying my head off about what he thinks. I can‚Äôt help what he thinks; it‚Äôs too late for that. So why should I keep pestering myself about it?‚Äù

‚ÄúIt‚Äôll wear off, Virgil,‚Äù Mrs.¬ÝAdams said, reassuringly. She was gentle and sympathetic with him, and for the first time in many years he would come to sit with her and talk, when he had finished his day‚Äôs work. He had told her, evading her eye, ‚ÄúOh, I don‚Äôt blame you. You didn‚Äôt get after me to do this on your own account; you couldn‚Äôt help it.‚Äù

‚ÄúYes; but it don‚Äôt wear off,‚Äù he complained. ‚ÄúThis afternoon I was showing the men how I wanted my vats to go, and I caught my fool self standing there saying to my fool self, ‚ÄòIt‚Äôs funny I don‚Äôt hear how he feels about it from somebody.‚Äô I was saying it aloud, almost‚ÅÝ‚Äîand it is funny I don‚Äôt hear anything!‚Äù

‚ÄúWell, you see what it means, don‚Äôt you, Virgil? It only means he hasn‚Äôt said anything to anybody about it. Don‚Äôt you think you‚Äôre getting kind of morbid over it?‚Äù

‚ÄúMaybe, maybe,‚Äù he muttered.

‚ÄúWhy, yes,‚Äù she said, briskly. ‚ÄúYou don‚Äôt realize what a little bit of a thing all this is to him. It‚Äôs been a long, long while since the last time you even mentioned glue to him, and he‚Äôs probably forgotten everything about it.‚Äù

‚ÄúYou‚Äôre off your base; it isn‚Äôt like him to forget things,‚Äù Adams returned, peevishly. ‚ÄúHe may seem to forget ‚Äôem, but he don‚Äôt.‚Äù

‚ÄúBut he‚Äôs not thinking about this, or you‚Äôd have heard from him before now.‚Äù

Her husband shook his head. ‚ÄúAh, that‚Äôs just it!‚Äù he said. ‚ÄúWhy haven‚Äôt I heard from him?‚Äù

‚ÄúIt‚Äôs all your morbidness, Virgil. Look at Walter: if Mr.¬ÝLamb held this up against you, would he still let Walter stay there? Wouldn‚Äôt he have discharged Walter if he felt angry with you?‚Äù

‚ÄúThat dang boy!‚Äù Adams said. ‚ÄúIf he wanted to come with me now, I wouldn‚Äôt hardly let him, What do you suppose makes him so bullheaded?‚Äù

‚ÄúBut hasn‚Äôt he a right to choose for himself?‚Äù she asked. ‚ÄúI suppose he feels he ought to stick to what he thinks is sure pay. As soon as he sees that you‚Äôre going to succeed with the glue-works he‚Äôll want to be with you quick enough.‚Äù

‚ÄúWell, he better get a little sense in his head,‚Äù Adams returned, crossly. ‚ÄúHe wanted me to pay him a three-hundred-dollar bonus in advance, when anybody with a grain of common sense knows I need every penny I can lay my hands on!‚Äù

‚ÄúNever mind,‚Äù she said. ‚ÄúHe‚Äôll come around later and be glad of the chance.‚Äù

‚ÄúHe‚Äôll have to beg for it then! I won‚Äôt ask him again.‚Äù

‚ÄúOh, Walter will come out all right; you needn‚Äôt worry. And don‚Äôt you see that Mr.¬ÝLamb‚Äôs not discharging him means there‚Äôs no hard feeling against you, Virgil?‚Äù

‚ÄúI can‚Äôt make it out at all,‚Äù he said, frowning. ‚ÄúThe only thing I can think it means is that J. A. Lamb is so fair-minded‚ÅÝ‚Äîand of course he is one of the fair-mindedest men alive‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI suppose that‚Äôs the reason he hasn‚Äôt fired Walter. He may know,‚Äù Adams concluded, morosely‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äúhe may know that‚Äôs just another thing to make me feel all the meaner: keeping my boy there on a salary after I‚Äôve done him an injury.‚Äù

‚ÄúNow, now!‚Äù she said, trying to comfort him. ‚ÄúYou couldn‚Äôt do anybody an injury to save your life, and everybody knows it.‚Äù

‚ÄúWell, anybody ought to know I wouldn‚Äôt want to do an injury, but this world isn‚Äôt built so‚Äôt we can do just what we want.‚Äù He paused, reflecting. ‚ÄúOf course there may be one explanation of why Walter‚Äôs still there: J. A. maybe hasn‚Äôt noticed that he is there. There‚Äôs so many I expect he hardly knows him by sight.‚Äù

‚ÄúWell, just do quit thinking about it,‚Äù she urged him. ‚ÄúIt only bothers you without doing any good. Don‚Äôt you know that?‚Äù

‚ÄúDon‚Äôt I, though!‚Äù he laughed, feebly. ‚ÄúI know it better‚Äôn anybody! How funny that is: when you know thinking about a thing only pesters you without helping anything at all, and yet you keep right on pestering yourself with it!‚Äù

‚ÄúBut why?‚Äù she said. ‚ÄúWhat‚Äôs the use when you know you haven‚Äôt done anything wrong, Virgil? You said yourself you were going to improve the process so much it would be different from the old one, and you‚Äôd really have a right to it.‚Äù

Adams had persuaded himself of this when he yielded; he had found it necessary to persuade himself of it‚ÅÝ‚Äîthough there was a part of him, of course, that remained unpersuaded; and this discomfiting part of him was what made his present trouble. ‚ÄúYes, I know,‚Äù he said. ‚ÄúThat‚Äôs true, but I can‚Äôt quite seem to get away from the fact that the principle of the process is a good deal the same‚ÅÝ‚Äîwell, it‚Äôs more‚Äôn that; it‚Äôs just about the same as the one he hired Campbell and me to work out for him. Truth is, nobody could tell the difference, and I don‚Äôt know as there is any difference except in these improvements I‚Äôm making. Of course, the improvements do give me pretty near a perfect right to it, as a person might say; and that‚Äôs one of the things I thought of putting in my letter to him; but I was afraid he‚Äôd just think I was trying to make up excuses, so I left it out. I kind of worried all the time I was writing that letter, because if he thought I was just making up excuses, why, it might set him just so much more against me.‚Äù

Ever since Mrs.¬ÝAdams had found that she was to have her way, the depths of her eyes had been troubled by a continuous uneasiness; and, although she knew it was there, and sometimes veiled it by keeping the revealing eyes averted from her husband and children, she could not always cover it under that assumption of absentmindedness. The uneasy look became vivid, and her voice was slightly tremulous now, as she said, ‚ÄúBut what if he should be against you‚ÅÝ‚Äîalthough I don‚Äôt believe he is, of course‚ÅÝ‚Äîyou told me he couldn‚Äôt do anything to you, Virgil.‚Äù

‚ÄúNo,‚Äù he said, slowly. ‚ÄúI can‚Äôt see how he could do anything. It was just a secret, not a patent; the thing ain‚Äôt patentable. I‚Äôve tried to think what he could do‚ÅÝ‚Äîsupposing he was to want to‚ÅÝ‚Äîbut I can‚Äôt figure out anything at all that would be any harm to me. There isn‚Äôt any way in the world it could be made a question of law. Only thing he could do‚Äôd be to tell people his side of it, and set ‚Äôem against me. I been kind of waiting for that to happen, all along.‚Äù

She looked somewhat relieved. ‚ÄúSo did I expect it,‚Äù she said. ‚ÄúI was dreading it most on Alice‚Äôs account: it might have‚ÅÝ‚Äîwell, young men are so easily influenced and all. But so far as the business is concerned, what if Mr.¬ÝLamb did talk? That wouldn‚Äôt amount to much. It wouldn‚Äôt affect the business; not to hurt. And, besides, he isn‚Äôt even doing that.‚Äù

‚ÄúNo; anyhow not yet, it seems.‚Äù And Adams sighed again, wistfully. ‚ÄúBut I would give a good deal to know what he thinks!‚Äù

Before his surrender he had always supposed that if he did such an unthinkable thing as to seize upon the glue process for himself, what he would feel must be an overpowering shame. But shame is the rarest thing in the world: what he felt was this unremittent curiosity about his old employer‚Äôs thoughts. It was an obsession, yet he did not want to hear what Lamb ‚Äúthought‚Äù from Lamb himself, for Adams had a second obsession, and this was his dread of meeting the old man face to face. Such an encounter could happen only by chance and unexpectedly; since Adams would have avoided any deliberate meeting, so long as his legs had strength to carry him, even if Lamb came to the house to see him.

But people do meet unexpectedly; and when Adams had to be downtown he kept away from the ‚Äúwholesale district.‚Äù One day he did see Lamb, as the latter went by in his car, impassive, going home to lunch; and Adams, in the crowd at a corner, knew that the old man had not seen him. Nevertheless, in a street car, on the way back to his sheds, an hour later, he was still subject to little shivering seizures of horror.

He worked unceasingly, seeming to keep at it even in his sleep, for he always woke in the midst of a planning and estimating that must have been going on in his mind before consciousness of himself returned. Moreover, the work, thus urged, went rapidly, in spite of the high wages he had to pay his labourers for their short hours. ‚ÄúIt eats money,‚Äù he complained, and, in fact, by the time his vats and boilers were in place it had eaten almost all he could supply; but in addition to his equipment he now owned a stock of ‚Äúraw material,‚Äù raw indeed; and when operations should be a little further along he was confident his banker would be willing to ‚Äúcarry‚Äù him.

Six weeks from the day he had obtained his lease he began his glue-making. The terrible smells came out of the sheds and went writhing like snakes all through that quarter of the town. A smiling man, strolling and breathing the air with satisfaction, would turn a corner and smile no more, but hurry. However, coloured people had almost all the dwellings of this old section to themselves; and although even they were troubled, there was recompense for them. Being philosophic about what appeared to them as in the order of nature, they sought neither escape nor redress, and soon learned to bear what the wind brought them. They even made use of it to enrich those figures of speech with which the native impulses of coloured people decorate their communications: they flavoured metaphor, simile, and invective with it; and thus may be said to have enjoyed it. But the man who produced it took a hot bath as soon as he reached his home the evening of that first day when his manufacturing began. Then he put on fresh clothes; but after dinner he seemed to be haunted, and asked his wife if she ‚Äúnoticed anything.‚Äù

She laughed and inquired what he meant.

‚ÄúSeems to me as if that glue-works smell hadn‚Äôt quit hanging to me,‚Äù he explained. ‚ÄúDon‚Äôt you notice it?‚Äù

‚ÄúNo! What an idea!‚Äù

He laughed, too, but uneasily; and told her he was sure ‚Äúthe dang glue smell‚Äù was somehow sticking to him. Later, he went outdoors and walked up and down the small yard in the dusk; but now and then he stood still, with his head lifted, and sniffed the air suspiciously. ‚ÄúCan you smell it?‚Äù he called to Alice, who sat upon the veranda, prettily dressed and waiting in a reverie.

‚ÄúSmell what, papa?‚Äù

‚ÄúThat dang glue-works.‚Äù

She did the same thing her mother had done: laughed, and said, ‚ÄúNo! How foolish! Why, papa, it‚Äôs over two miles from here!‚Äù

‚ÄúYou don‚Äôt get it at all?‚Äù he insisted.

‚ÄúThe idea! The air is lovely tonight, papa.‚Äù

The air did not seem lovely to him, for he was positive that he detected the taint. He wondered how far it carried, and if J. A. Lamb would smell it, too, out on his own lawn a mile to the north; and if he did, would he guess what it was? Then Adams laughed at himself for such nonsense; but could not rid his nostrils of their disgust. To him the whole town seemed to smell of his glue-works.

Nevertheless, the glue was making, and his sheds were busy. ‚ÄúGuess we‚Äôre stirrin‚Äô up this ole neighbourhood with more than the smell,‚Äù his foreman remarked one morning.

‚ÄúHow‚Äôs that?‚Äù Adams inquired.

‚ÄúThat great big, enormous ole dead butterine factory across the street from our lot,‚Äù the man said. ‚ÄúNothin‚Äô like settin‚Äô an example to bring real estate to life. That place is full o‚Äô carpenters startin‚Äô in to make a regular buildin‚Äô of it again. Guess you ought to have the credit of it, because you was the first man in ten years to see any possibilities in this neighbourhood.‚Äù

Adams was pleased, and, going out to see for himself, heard a great hammering and sawing from within the building; while carpenters were just emerging gingerly upon the dangerous roof. He walked out over the dried mud of his deep lot, crossed the street, and spoke genially to a workman who was removing the broken glass of a window on the ground floor.

‚ÄúHere! What‚Äôs all this howdy-do over here?‚Äù

‚ÄúGoin‚Äô to fix her all up, I guess,‚Äù the workman said. ‚ÄúBig job it is, too.‚Äù

‚ÄúSh‚Äô think it would be.‚Äù

‚ÄúYes, sir; a pretty big job‚ÅÝ‚Äîa pretty big job. Got men at it on all four floors and on the roof. They‚Äôre doin‚Äô it right.‚Äù

‚ÄúWho‚Äôs doing it?‚Äù

‚ÄúLord! I d‚Äô know. Some o‚Äô these here big manufacturing corporations, I guess.‚Äù

‚ÄúWhat‚Äôs it going to be?‚Äù

‚ÄúThey tell me,‚Äù the workman answered‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äúthey tell me she‚Äôs goin‚Äô to be a butterine factory again. Anyways, I hope she won‚Äôt be anything to smell like that glue-works you got over there not while I‚Äôm workin‚Äô around her, anyways!‚Äù

‚ÄúThat smell‚Äôs all right,‚Äù Adams said. ‚ÄúYou soon get used to it.‚Äù

‚ÄúYou do?‚Äù The man appeared incredulous. ‚ÄúListen! I was over in France: it‚Äôs a good thing them Dutchmen never thought of it; we‚Äôd of had to quit!‚Äù

Adams laughed, and went back to his sheds. ‚ÄúI guess my foreman was right,‚Äù he told his wife, that evening, with a little satisfaction. ‚ÄúAs soon as one man shows enterprise enough to found an industry in a broken-down neighbourhood, somebody else is sure to follow. I kind of like the look of it: it‚Äôll help make our place seem sort of more busy and prosperous when it comes to getting a loan from the bank‚ÅÝ‚Äîand I got to get one mighty soon, too. I did think some that if things go as well as there‚Äôs every reason to think they ought to, I might want to spread out and maybe get hold of that old factory myself; but I hardly expected to be able to handle a proposition of that size before two or three years from now, and anyhow there‚Äôs room enough on the lot I got, if we need more buildings someday. Things are going about as fine as I could ask: I hired some girls today to do the bottling‚ÅÝ‚Äîcoloured girls along about sixteen to twenty years old. Afterwhile, I expect to get a machine to put the stuff in the little bottles, when we begin to get good returns; but half a dozen of these coloured girls can do it all right now, by hand. We‚Äôre getting to have really quite a little plant over there: yes, sir, quite a regular little plant!‚Äù

He chuckled, and at this cheerful sound, of a kind his wife had almost forgotten he was capable of producing, she ventured to put her hand upon his arm. They had gone outdoors, after dinner, taking two chairs with them, and were sitting through the late twilight together, keeping well away from the front porch, which was not yet occupied, however. Alice was in her room changing her dress.

‚ÄúWell, honey,‚Äù Mrs.¬ÝAdams said, taking confidence not only to put her hand upon his arm, but to revive this disused endearment;‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äúit‚Äôs grand to have you so optimistic. Maybe some time you‚Äôll admit I was right, after all. Everything‚Äôs going so well, it seems a pity you didn‚Äôt take this‚ÅÝ‚Äîthis step‚ÅÝ‚Äîlong ago. Don‚Äôt you think maybe so, Virgil?‚Äù

‚ÄúWell‚ÅÝ‚Äîif I was ever going to, I don‚Äôt know but I might as well of. I got to admit the proposition begins to look pretty good: I know the stuff‚Äôll sell, and I can‚Äôt see a thing in the world to stop it. It does look good, and if‚ÅÝ‚Äîif‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù He paused.

‚ÄúIf what?‚Äù she said, suddenly anxious.

He laughed plaintively, as if confessing a superstition. ‚ÄúIt‚Äôs funny‚ÅÝ‚Äîwell, it‚Äôs mighty funny about that smell. I‚Äôve got so used to it at the plant I never seem to notice it at all over there. It‚Äôs only when I get away. Honestly, can‚Äôt you notice‚ÅÝ‚Äî?‚Äù

‚ÄúVirgil!‚Äù She lifted her hand to strike his arm chidingly. ‚ÄúDo quit harping on that nonsense!‚Äù

‚ÄúOh, of course it don‚Äôt amount to anything,‚Äù he said. ‚ÄúA person can stand a good deal of just smell. It don‚Äôt worry me any.‚Äù

‚ÄúI should think not especially as there isn‚Äôt any.‚Äù

‚ÄúWell,‚Äù he said, ‚ÄúI feel pretty fair over the whole thing‚ÅÝ‚Äîa lot better‚Äôn I ever expected to, anyhow. I don‚Äôt know as there‚Äôs any reason I shouldn‚Äôt tell you so.‚Äù

She was deeply pleased with this acknowledgment, and her voice had tenderness in it as she responded: ‚ÄúThere, honey! Didn‚Äôt I always say you‚Äôd be glad if you did it?‚Äù

Embarrassed, he coughed loudly, then filled his pipe and lit it. ‚ÄúWell,‚Äù he said, slowly, ‚Äúit‚Äôs a puzzle. Yes, sir, it‚Äôs a puzzle.‚Äù

‚ÄúWhat is?‚Äù

‚ÄúPretty much everything, I guess.‚Äù

As he spoke, a song came to them from a lighted window over their heads. Then the window darkened abruptly, but the song continued as Alice went down through the house to wait on the little veranda. ‚ÄúMi chiamo Mimi,‚Äù she sang, and in her voice throbbed something almost startling in its sweetness. Her father and mother listened, not speaking until the song stopped with the click of the wire screen at the front door as Alice came out.

‚ÄúMy!‚Äù said her father. ‚ÄúHow sweet she does sing! I don‚Äôt know as I ever heard her voice sound nicer than it did just then.‚Äù

‚ÄúThere‚Äôs something that makes it sound that way,‚Äù his wife told him.

‚ÄúI suppose so,‚Äù he said, sighing. ‚ÄúI suppose so. You think‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù

‚ÄúShe‚Äôs just terribly in love with him!‚Äù

‚ÄúI expect that‚Äôs the way it ought to be,‚Äù he said, then drew upon his pipe for reflection, and became murmurous with the symptoms of melancholy laughter. ‚ÄúIt don‚Äôt make things less of a puzzle, though, does it?‚Äù

‚ÄúIn what way, Virgil?‚Äù

‚ÄúWhy, here,‚Äù he said‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äúhere we go through all this muck and moil to help fix things nicer for her at home, and what‚Äôs it all amount to? Seems like she‚Äôs just gone ahead the way she‚Äôd ‚Äôa‚Äô gone anyhow; and now, I suppose, getting ready to up and leave us! Ain‚Äôt that a puzzle to you? It is to me.‚Äù

‚ÄúOh, but things haven‚Äôt gone that far yet.‚Äù

‚ÄúWhy, you just said‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù

She gave a little cry of protest. ‚ÄúOh, they aren‚Äôt engaged yet. Of course they will be; he‚Äôs just as much interested in her as she is in him, but‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù

‚ÄúWell, what‚Äôs the trouble then?‚Äù

‚ÄúYou are a simple old fellow!‚Äù his wife exclaimed, and then rose from her chair. ‚ÄúThat reminds me,‚Äù she said.

‚ÄúWhat of?‚Äù he asked. ‚ÄúWhat‚Äôs my being simple remind you of?‚Äù

‚ÄúNothing!‚Äù she laughed. ‚ÄúIt wasn‚Äôt you that reminded me. It was just something that‚Äôs been on my mind. I don‚Äôt believe he‚Äôs actually ever been inside our house!‚Äù

‚ÄúHasn‚Äôt he?‚Äù

‚ÄúI actually don‚Äôt believe he ever has,‚Äù she said. ‚ÄúOf course we must‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù She paused, debating.

‚ÄúWe must what?‚Äù

‚ÄúI guess I better talk to Alice about it right now,‚Äù she said. ‚ÄúHe don‚Äôt usually come for about half an hour yet; I guess I‚Äôve got time.‚Äù And with that she walked away, leaving him to his puzzles.

XXII

Alice kept her sprightly chatter going when they sat down, though the temperature of the room and the sight of hot soup might have discouraged a less determined gayety. Moreover, there were details as unpropitious as the heat: the expiring roses expressed not beauty but pathos, and what faint odour they exhaled was no rival to the lusty emanations of the Brussels sprouts; at the head of the table, Adams, sitting low in his chair, appeared to be unable to flatten the uprising wave of his starched bosom; and Gertrude’s manner and expression were of a recognizable hostility during the long period of vain waiting for the cups of soup to be emptied. Only Mrs. Adams made any progress in this direction; the others merely feinting, now and then lifting their spoons as if they intended to do something with them.

Alice’s talk was little more than cheerful sound, but, to fill a desolate interval, served its purpose; and her mother supported her with ever-faithful cooings of applausive laughter. “What a funny thing weather is!” the girl ran on. “Yesterday it was cool—angels had charge of it—and today they had an engagement somewhere else, so the devil saw his chance and started to move the equator to the North Pole; but by the time he got halfway, he thought of something else he wanted to do, and went off; and left the equator here, right on top of us! I wish he’d come back and get it!”

“Why, Alice dear!” her mother cried, fondly. “What an imagination! Not a very pious one, I’m afraid Mr. Russell might think, though!” Here she gave Gertrude a hidden signal to remove the soup; but, as there was no response, she had to make the signal more conspicuous. Gertrude was leaning against the wall, her chin moving like a slow pendulum, her streaked eyes fixed mutinously upon Russell. Mrs. Adams nodded several times, increasing the emphasis of her gesture, while Alice talked briskly; but the brooding waitress continued to brood. A faint snap of the fingers failed to disturb her; nor was a covert hissing whisper of avail, and Mrs. Adams was beginning to show signs of strain when her daughter relieved her.

“Imagine our trying to eat anything so hot as soup on a night like this!” Alice laughed. “What could have been in the cook’s mind not to give us something iced and jellied instead? Of course it’s because she’s equatorial, herself, originally, and only feels at home when Mr. Satan moves it north.” She looked round at Gertrude, who stood behind her. “Do take this dreadful soup away!”

Thus directly addressed, Gertrude yielded her attention, though unwillingly, and as if she decided only by a hair’s weight not to revolt, instead. However, she finally set herself in slow motion; but overlooked the supposed head of the table, seeming to be unaware of the sweltering little man who sat there. As she disappeared toward the kitchen with but three of the cups upon her tray he turned to look plaintively after her, and ventured an attempt to recall her.

“Here!” he said, in a low voice. “Here, you!”

“What is it, Virgil?” his wife asked.

“What’s her name?”

Mrs. Adams gave him a glance of sudden panic, and, seeing that the guest of the evening was not looking at her, but down at the white cloth before him, she frowned hard, and shook her head.

Unfortunately Alice was not observing her mother, and asked, innocently: “What’s whose name, papa?”

“Why, this young darky woman,” he explained. “She left mine.”

“Never mind,” Alice laughed. “There’s hope for you, papa. She hasn’t gone forever!”

“I don’t know about that,” he said, not content with this impulsive assurance. “She looked like she is.” And his remark, considered as a prediction, had begun to seem warranted before Gertrude’s return with china preliminary to the next stage of the banquet.

Alice proved herself equal to the long gap, and rattled on through it with a spirit richly justifying her mother’s praise of her as “always ready to smooth things over”; for here was more than long delay to be smoothed over. She smoothed over her father and mother for Russell; and she smoothed over him for them, though he did not know it, and remained unaware of what he owed her. With all this, throughout her prattlings, the girl’s bright eyes kept seeking his with an eager gayety, which but little veiled both interrogation and entreaty—as if she asked: “Is it too much for you? Can’t you bear it? Won’t you please bear it? I would for you. Won’t you give me a sign that it’s all right?”

He looked at her but fleetingly, and seemed to suffer from the heat, in spite of every manly effort not to wipe his brow too often. His colour, after rising when he greeted Alice and her father, had departed, leaving him again moistly pallid; a condition arising from discomfort, no doubt, but, considered as a decoration, almost poetically becoming to him. Not less becoming was the faint, kindly smile, which showed his wish to express amusement and approval; and yet it was a smile rather strained and plaintive, as if he, like Adams, could only do the best he could.

He pleased Adams, who thought him a fine young man, and decidedly the quietest that Alice had ever shown to her family. In her father’s opinion this was no small merit; and it was to Russell’s credit, too, that he showed embarrassment upon this first intimate presentation; here was an applicant with both reserve and modesty. “So far, he seems to be first rate a mighty fine young man,” Adams thought; and, prompted by no wish to part from Alice but by reminiscences of apparent candidates less pleasing, he added, “At last!”

Alice’s liveliness never flagged. Her smoothing over of things was an almost continuous performance, and had to be. Yet, while she chattered through the hot and heavy courses, the questions she asked herself were as continuous as the performance, and as poignant as what her eyes seemed to be asking Russell. Why had she not prevailed over her mother’s fear of being “skimpy?” Had she been, indeed, as her mother said she looked, “in a trance?” But above all: What was the matter with him? What had happened? For she told herself with painful humour that something even worse than this dinner must be “the matter with him.”

The small room, suffocated with the odour of boiled sprouts, grew hotter and hotter as more and more food appeared, slowly borne in, between deathly long waits, by the resentful, loud-breathing Gertrude. And while Alice still sought Russell’s glance, and read the look upon his face a dozen different ways, fearing all of them; and while the straggling little flowers died upon the stained cloth, she felt her heart grow as heavy as the food, and wondered that it did not die like the roses.

With the arrival of coffee, the host bestirred himself to make known a hospitable regret, “By George!” he said. “I meant to buy some cigars.” He addressed himself apologetically to the guest. “I don’t know what I was thinking about, to forget to bring some home with me. I don’t use ’em myself—unless somebody hands me one, you might say. I’ve always been a pipe-smoker, pure and simple, but I ought to remembered for kind of an occasion like this.”

“Not at all,” Russell said. “I’m not smoking at all lately; but when I do, I’m like you, and smoke a pipe.”

Alice started, remembering what she had told him when he overtook her on her way from the tobacconist’s; but, after a moment, looking at him, she decided that he must have forgotten it. If he had remembered, she thought, he could not have helped glancing at her. On the contrary, he seemed more at ease, just then, than he had since they sat down, for he was favouring her father with a thoughtful attention as Adams responded to the introduction of a man’s topic into the conversation at last. “Well, Mr. Russell, I guess you’re right, at that. I don’t say but what cigars may be all right for a man that can afford ’em, if he likes ’em better than a pipe, but you take a good old pipe now—”

He continued, and was getting well into the eulogium customarily provoked by this theme, when there came an interruption: the doorbell rang, and he paused inquiringly, rather surprised.

Mrs. Adams spoke to Gertrude in an undertone:

“Just say, ‘Not at home.’ ”

“What?”

“If it’s callers, just say we’re not at home.”

Gertrude spoke out freely: “You mean you astin’ me to ’tend you’ front do’ fer you?”

She seemed both incredulous and affronted, but Mrs. Adams persisted, though somewhat apprehensively. “Yes. Hurry—uh—please. Just say we’re not at home if you please.”

Again Gertrude obviously hesitated between compliance and revolt, and again the meeker course fortunately prevailed with her. She gave Mrs. Adams a stare, grimly derisive, then departed. When she came back she said:

“He say he wait.”

“But I told you to tell anybody we were not at home,” Mrs. Adams returned. “Who is it?”

“Say he name Mr. Law.”

“We don’t know any Mr. Law.”

“Yes’m; he know you. Say he anxious to speak Mr. Adams. Say he wait.”

“Tell him Mr. Adams is engaged.”

“Hold on a minute,” Adams intervened. “Law? No. I don’t know any Mr. Law. You sure you got the name right?”

“Say he name Law,” Gertrude replied, looking at the ceiling to express her fatigue. “Law. ’S all he tell me; ’s all I know.”

Adams frowned. “Law,” he said. “Wasn’t it maybe ‘Lohr’?”

“Law,” Gertrude repeated. “ ’S all he tell me; ’s all I know.”

“What’s he look like?”

“He ain’t much,” she said. “ ’Bout you’ age; got brustly white moustache, nice eyeglasses.”

“It’s Charley Lohr!” Adams exclaimed. “I’ll go see what he wants.”

“But, Virgil,” his wife remonstrated, “do finish your coffee; he might stay all evening. Maybe he’s come to call.”

Adams laughed. “He isn’t much of a caller, I expect. Don’t worry: I’ll take him up to my room.” And turning toward Russell, “Ah—if you’ll just excuse me,” he said; and went out to his visitor.

When he had gone, Mrs. Adams finished her coffee, and, having glanced intelligently from her guest to her daughter, she rose. “I think perhaps I ought to go and shake hands with Mr. Lohr, myself,” she said, adding in explanation to Russell, as she reached the door, “He’s an old friend of my husband’s and it’s a very long time since he’s been here.”

Alice nodded and smiled to her brightly, but upon the closing of the door, the smile vanished; all her liveliness disappeared; and with this change of expression her complexion itself appeared to change, so that her rouge became obvious, for she was pale beneath it. However, Russell did not see the alteration, for he did not look at her; and it was but a momentary lapse the vacation of a tired girl, who for ten seconds lets herself look as she feels. Then she shot her vivacity back into place as by some powerful spring.

“Penny for your thoughts!” she cried, and tossed one of the wilted roses at him, across the table. “I’ll bid more than a penny; I’ll bid tuppence—no, a poor little dead rose—a rose for your thoughts, Mr. Arthur Russell! What are they?”

He shook his head. “I’m afraid I haven’t any.”

“No, of course not,” she said. “Who could have thoughts in weather like this? Will you ever forgive us?”

“What for?”

“Making you eat such a heavy dinner—I mean look at such a heavy dinner, because you certainly didn’t do more than look at it—on such a night! But the crime draws to a close, and you can begin to cheer up!” She laughed gaily, and, rising, moved to the door. “Let’s go in the other room; your fearful duty is almost done, and you can run home as soon as you want to. That’s what you’re dying to do.”

“Not at all,” he said in a voice so feeble that she laughed aloud.

“Good gracious!” she cried. “I hadn’t realized it was that bad!”

For this, though he contrived to laugh, he seemed to have no verbal retort whatever; but followed her into the living-room, where she stopped and turned, facing him.

“Has it really been so frightful?” she asked.

“Why, of course not. Not at all.”

“Of course yes, though, you mean!”

“Not at all. It’s been most kind of your mother and father and you.”

“Do you know,” she said, “you’ve never once looked at me for more than a second at a time the whole evening? And it seemed to me I looked rather nice tonight, too!”

“You always do,” he murmured.

“I don’t see how you know,” she returned; and then stepping closer to him, spoke with gentle solicitude: “Tell me: you’re really feeling wretchedly, aren’t you? I know you’ve got a fearful headache, or something. Tell me!”

“Not at all.”

“You are ill—I’m sure of it.”

“Not at all.”

“On your word?”

“I’m really quite all right.”

“But if you are—” she began; and then, looking at him with a desperate sweetness, as if this were her last resource to rouse him, “What’s the matter, little boy?” she said with lisping tenderness. “Tell auntie!”

It was a mistake, for he seemed to flinch, and to lean backward, however, slightly. She turned away instantly, with a flippant lift and drop of both hands. “Oh, my dear!” she laughed. “I won’t eat you!”

And as the discomfited young man watched her, seeming able to lift his eyes, now that her back was turned, she went to the front door and pushed open the screen. “Let’s go out on the porch,” she said. “Where we belong!”

Then, when he had followed her out, and they were seated, “Isn’t this better?” she asked. “Don’t you feel more like yourself out here?”

He began a murmur: “Not at—”

But she cut him off sharply: “Please don’t say ‘Not at all’ again!”

“I’m sorry.”

“You do seem sorry about something,” she said. “What is it? Isn’t it time you were telling me what’s the matter?”

“Nothing. Indeed nothing’s the matter. Of course one is rather affected by such weather as this. It may make one a little quieter than usual, of course.”

She sighed, and let the tired muscles of her face rest. Under the hard lights, indoors, they had served her until they ached, and it was a luxury to feel that in the darkness no grimacings need call upon them.

“Of course, if you won’t tell me—” she said.

“I can only assure you there’s nothing to tell.”

“I know what an ugly little house it is,” she said. “Maybe it was the furniture—or mama’s vases that upset you. Or was it mama herself—or papa?”

“Nothing ‘upset’ me.”

At that she uttered a monosyllable of doubting laughter. “I wonder why you say that.”

“Because it’s so.”

“No. It’s because you’re too kind, or too conscientious, or too embarrassed—anyhow too something—to tell me.” She leaned forward, elbows on knees and chin in hands, in the reflective attitude she knew how to make graceful. “I have a feeling that you’re not going to tell me,” she said, slowly. “Yes—even that you’re never going to tell me. I wonder—I wonder—”

“Yes? What do you wonder?”

“I was just thinking—I wonder if they haven’t done it, after all.”

“I don’t understand.”

“I wonder,” she went on, still slowly, and in a voice of reflection, “I wonder who has been talking about me to you, after all? Isn’t that it?”

“Not at—” he began, but checked himself and substituted another form of denial. “Nothing is ‘it.’ ”

“Are you sure?”

“Why, yes.”

“How curious!” she said.

“Why?”

“Because all evening you’ve been so utterly different.”

“But in this weather—”

“No. That wouldn’t make you afraid to look at me all evening!”

“But I did look at you. Often.”

“No. Not really a look.”

“But I’m looking at you now.”

“Yes—in the dark!” she said. “No—the weather might make you even quieter than usual, but it wouldn’t strike you so nearly dumb. No—and it wouldn’t make you seem to be under such a strain—as if you thought only of escape!”

“But I haven’t—”

“You shouldn’t,” she interrupted, gently. “There’s nothing you have to escape from, you know. You aren’t committed to—to this friendship.”

“I’m sorry you think—” he began, but did not complete the fragment.

She took it up. “You’re sorry I think you’re so different, you mean to say, don’t you? Never mind: that’s what you did mean to say, but you couldn’t finish it because you’re not good at deceiving.”

“Oh, no,” he protested, feebly. “I’m not deceiving. I’m—”

“Never mind,” she said again. “You’re sorry I think you’re so different—and all in one day—since last night. Yes, your voice sounds sorry, too. It sounds sorrier than it would just because of my thinking something you could change my mind about in a minute so it means you’re sorry you are different.”

“No—I—”

But disregarding the faint denial, “Never mind,” she said. “Do you remember one night when you told me that nothing anybody else could do would ever keep you from coming here? That if you—if you left me it would be because I drove you away myself?”

“Yes,” he said, huskily. “It was true.”

“Are you sure?”

“Indeed I am,” he answered in a low voice, but with conviction.

“Then—” She paused. “Well—but I haven’t driven you away.”

“No.”

“And yet you’ve gone,” she said, quietly.

“Do I seem so stupid as all that?”

“You know what I mean.” She leaned back in her chair again, and her hands, inactive for once, lay motionless in her lap. When she spoke it was in a rueful whisper:

“I wonder if I have driven you away?”

“You’ve done nothing—nothing at all,” he said.

“I wonder—” she said once more, but she stopped. In her mind she was going back over their time together since the first meeting—fragments of talk, moments of silence, little things of no importance, little things that might be important; moonshine, sunshine, starlight; and her thoughts zigzagged among the jumbling memories; but, as if she made for herself a picture of all these fragments, throwing them upon the canvas haphazard, she saw them all just touched with the one tainting quality that gave them coherence, the faint, false haze she had put over this friendship by her own pretendings. And, if this terrible dinner, or anything, or everything, had shown that saffron tint in its true colour to the man at her side, last night almost a lover, then she had indeed of herself driven him away, and might well feel that she was lost.

“Do you know?” she said, suddenly, in a clear, loud voice. “I have the strangest feeling. I feel as if I were going to be with you only about five minutes more in all the rest of my life!”

“Why, no,” he said. “Of course I’m coming to see you—often. I—”

“No,” she interrupted. “I’ve never had a feeling like this before. It’s—it’s just so; that’s all! You’re going—why, you’re never coming here again!” She stood up, abruptly, beginning to tremble all over. “Why, it’s finished, isn’t it?” she said, and her trembling was manifest now in her voice. “Why, it’s all over, isn’t it? Why, yes!”

He had risen as she did. “I’m afraid you’re awfully tired and nervous,” he said. “I really ought to be going.”

“Yes, of course you ought,” she cried, despairingly. “There’s nothing else for you to do. When anything’s spoiled, people can’t do anything but run away from it. So goodbye!”

“At least,” he returned, huskily, “we’ll only—only say good night.”

Then, as moving to go, he stumbled upon the veranda steps, “Your hat!” she cried. “I’d like to keep it for a souvenir, but I’m afraid you need it!”

She ran into the hall and brought his straw hat from the chair where he had left it. “You poor thing!” she said, with quavering laughter. “Don’t you know you can’t go without your hat?”

Then, as they faced each other for the short moment which both of them knew would be the last of all their veranda moments, Alice’s broken laughter grew louder. “What a thing to say!” she cried. “What a romantic parting—talking about hats!”

Her laughter continued as he turned away, but other sounds came from within the house, clearly audible with the opening of a door upstairs—a long and wailing cry of lamentation in the voice of Mrs. Adams. Russell paused at the steps, uncertain, but Alice waved to him to go on.

“Oh, don’t bother,” she said. “We have lots of that in this funny little old house! Goodbye!”

And as he went down the steps, she ran back into the house and closed the door heavily behind her.

XXIII

Her mother’s wailing could still be heard from overhead, though more faintly; and old Charley Lohr was coming down the stairs alone.

He looked at Alice compassionately. “I was just comin’ to suggest maybe you’d excuse yourself from your company,” he said. “Your mother was bound not to disturb you, and tried her best to keep you from hearin’ how she’s takin’ on, but I thought probably you better see to her.”

“Yes, I’ll come. What’s the matter?”

“Well,” he said, “I only stepped over to offer my sympathy and services, as it were. I thought of course you folks knew all about it. Fact is, it was in the evening paper—just a little bit of an item on the back page, of course.”

“What is it?”

He coughed. “Well, it ain’t anything so terrible,” he said. “Fact is, your brother Walter’s got in a little trouble—well, I suppose you might call it quite a good deal of trouble. Fact is, he’s quite considerable short in his accounts down at Lamb and Company.”

Alice ran up the stairs and into her father’s room, where Mrs. Adams threw herself into her daughter’s arms. “Is he gone?” she sobbed. “He didn’t hear me, did he? I tried so hard—”

Alice patted the heaving shoulders her arms enclosed. “No, no,” she said. “He didn’t hear you—it wouldn’t have mattered—he doesn’t matter anyway.”

“Oh, poor Walter!” The mother cried. “Oh, the poor boy! Poor, poor Walter! Poor, poor, poor, poor—”

“Hush, dear, hush!” Alice tried to soothe her, but the lament could not be abated, and from the other side of the room a repetition in a different spirit was as continuous. Adams paced furiously there, pounding his fist into his left palm as he strode. “The dang boy!” he said. “Dang little fool! Dang idiot! Dang fool! Whyn’t he tell me, the dang little fool?”

“He did!” Mrs. Adams sobbed. “He did tell you, and you wouldn’t give it to him.”

“He did, did he?” Adams shouted at her. “What he begged me for was money to run away with! He never dreamed of putting back what he took. What the dangnation you talking about—accusing me!”

“He needed it,” she said. “He needed it to run away with! How could he expect to live, after he got away, if he didn’t have a little money? Oh, poor, poor, poor Walter! Poor, poor, poor—”

She went back to this repetition; and Adams went back to his own, then paused, seeing his old friend standing in the hallway outside the open door.

“Ah—I’ll just be goin’, I guess, Virgil,” Lohr said. “I don’t see as there’s any use my tryin’ to say any more. I’ll do anything you want me to, you understand.”

“Wait a minute,” Adams said, and, groaning, came and went down the stairs with him. “You say you didn’t see the old man at all?”

“No, I don’t know a thing about what he’s going to do,” Lohr said, as they reached the lower floor. “Not a thing. But look here, Virgil, I don’t see as this calls for you and your wife to take on so hard about—anyhow not as hard as the way you’ve started.”

“No,” Adams gulped. “It always seems that way to the other party that’s only looking on!”

“Oh, well, I know that, of course,” old Charley returned, soothingly. “But look here, Virgil: they may not catch the boy; they didn’t even seem to be sure what train he made, and if they do get him, why, the ole man might decide not to prosecute if—”

“Him?” Adams cried, interrupting. “Him not prosecute? Why, that’s what he’s been waiting for, all along! He thinks my boy and me both cheated him! Why, he was just letting Walter walk into a trap! Didn’t you say they’d been suspecting him for some time back? Didn’t you say they’d been watching him and were just about fixing to arrest him?”

“Yes, I know,” said Lohr; “but you can’t tell, especially if you raise the money and pay it back.”

“Every cent!” Adams vociferated. “Every last penny! I can raise it—I got to raise it! I’m going to put a loan on my factory tomorrow. Oh, I’ll get it for him, you tell him! Every last penny!”

“Well, ole feller, you just try and get quieted down some now.” Charley held out his hand in parting. “You and your wife just quiet down some. You ain’t the healthiest man in the world, you know, and you already been under quite some strain before this happened. You want to take care of yourself for the sake of your wife and that sweet little girl upstairs, you know. Now, good night,” he finished, stepping out upon the veranda. “You send for me if there’s anything I can do.”

“Do?” Adams echoed. “There ain’t anything anybody can do!” And then, as his old friend went down the path to the sidewalk, he called after him, “You tell him I’ll pay him every last cent! Every last, dang, dirty penny!”

He slammed the door and went rapidly up the stairs, talking loudly to himself. “Every dang, last, dirty penny! Thinks everybody in this family wants to steal from him, does he? Thinks we’re all yellow, does he? I’ll show him!” And he came into his own room vociferating, “Every last, dang, dirty penny!”

Mrs. Adams had collapsed, and Alice had put her upon his bed, where she lay tossing convulsively and sobbing, “Oh, poor Walter!” over and over, but after a time she varied the sorry tune. “Oh, poor Alice!” she moaned, clinging to her daughter’s hand. “Oh, poor, poor Alice to have this come on the night of your dinner—just when everything seemed to be going so well—at last—oh, poor, poor, poor—”

“Hush!” Alice said, sharply. “Don’t say ‘poor Alice’! I’m all right.”

“You must be!” her mother cried, clutching her. “You’ve just got to be! One of us has got to be all right—surely God wouldn’t mind just one of us being all right—that wouldn’t hurt Him—”

“Hush, hush, mother! Hush!”

But Mrs. Adams only clutched her the more tightly. “He seemed such a nice young man, dearie! He may not see this in the paper—Mr. Lohr said it was just a little bit of an item—he may not see it, dearie—”

Then her anguish went back to Walter again; and to his needs as a fugitive—she had meant to repair his underwear, but had postponed doing so, and her neglect now appeared to be a detail as lamentable as the calamity itself. She could neither be stilled upon it, nor herself exhaust its urgings to self-reproach, though she finally took up another theme temporarily. Upon an unusually violent outbreak of her husband’s, in denunciation of the runaway, she cried out faintly that he was cruel; and further wearied her broken voice with details of Walter’s beauty as a baby, and of his bedtime pieties throughout his infancy.

So the hot night wore on. Three had struck before Mrs. Adams was got to bed; and Alice, returning to her own room, could hear her father’s bare feet thudding back and forth after that. “Poor papa!” she whispered in helpless imitation of her mother. “Poor papa! Poor mama! Poor Walter! Poor all of us!”

She fell asleep, after a time, while from across the hall the bare feet still thudded over their changeless route; and she woke at seven, hearing Adams pass her door, shod. In her wrapper she ran out into the hallway and found him descending the stairs.

“Papa!”

“Hush,” he said, and looked up at her with reddened eyes. “Don’t wake your mother.”

“I won’t,” she whispered. “How about you? You haven’t slept any at all!”

“Yes, I did. I got some sleep. I’m going over to the works now. I got to throw some figures together to show the bank. Don’t worry: I’ll get things fixed up. You go back to bed. Goodbye.”

“Wait!” she bade him sharply.

“What for?”

“You’ve got to have some breakfast.”

“Don’t want ’ny.”

“You wait!” she said, imperiously, and disappeared to return almost at once. “I can cook in my bedroom slippers,” she explained, “but I don’t believe I could in my bare feet!”

Descending softly, she made him wait in the dining-room until she brought him toast and eggs and coffee. “Eat!” she said. “And I’m going to telephone for a taxicab to take you, if you think you’ve really got to go.”

“No, I’m going to walk—I want to walk.”

She shook her head anxiously. “You don’t look able. You’ve walked all night.”

“No, I didn’t,” he returned. “I tell you I got some sleep. I got all I wanted anyhow.”

“But, papa—”

“Here!” he interrupted, looking up at her suddenly and setting down his cup of coffee. “Look here! What about this Mr. Russell? I forgot all about him. What about him?”

Her lip trembled a little, but she controlled it before she spoke. “Well, what about him, papa?” she asked, calmly enough.

“Well, we could hardly—” Adams paused, frowning heavily. “We could hardly expect he wouldn’t hear something about all this.”

“Yes; of course he’ll hear it, papa.”

“Well?”

“Well, what?” she asked, gently.

“You don’t think he’d be the—the cheap kind it’d make a difference with, of course.”

“Oh, no; he isn’t cheap. It won’t make any difference with him.”

Adams suffered a profound sigh to escape him. “Well—I’m glad of that, anyway.”

“The difference,” she explained—“the difference was made without his hearing anything about Walter. He doesn’t know about that yet.”

“Well, what does he know about?”

“Only,” she said, “about me.”

“What you mean by that, Alice?” he asked, helplessly.

“Never mind,” she said. “It’s nothing beside the real trouble we’re in—I’ll tell you some time. You eat your eggs and toast; you can’t keep going on just coffee.”

“I can’t eat any eggs and toast,” he objected, rising. “I can’t.”

“Then wait till I can bring you something else.”

“No,” he said, irritably. “I won’t do it! I don’t want any dang food! And look here”—he spoke sharply to stop her, as she went toward the telephone—“I don’t want any dang taxi, either! You look after your mother when she wakes up. I got to be at work!”

And though she followed him to the front door, entreating, he could not be stayed or hindered. He went through the quiet morning streets at a rickety, rapid gait, swinging his old straw hat in his hands, and whispering angrily to himself as he went. His grizzled hair, not trimmed for a month, blew back from his damp forehead in the warm breeze; his reddened eyes stared hard at nothing from under blinking lids; and one side of his face twitched startlingly from time to time;—children might have run from him, or mocked him.

When he had come into that fallen quarter his industry had partly revived and wholly made odorous, a negro woman, leaning upon her whitewashed gate, gazed after him and chuckled for the benefit of a gossiping friend in the next tiny yard. “Oh, good Satan! Wha’ssa matter that ole glue man?”

“Who? Him?” the neighbour inquired. “What he do now?”

“Talkin’ to his ole se’f!” the first explained, joyously. “Look like gone distracted—ole glue man!”

Adams’s legs had grown more uncertain with his hard walk, and he stumbled heavily as he crossed the baked mud of his broad lot, but cared little for that, was almost unaware of it, in fact. Thus his eyes saw as little as his body felt, and so he failed to observe something that would have given him additional light upon an old phrase that already meant quite enough for him.

There are in the wide world people who have never learned its meaning; but most are either young or beautifully unobservant who remain wholly unaware of the inner poignancies the words convey: “a rain of misfortunes.” It is a boiling rain, seemingly whimsical in its choice of spots whereon to fall; and, so far as mortal eye can tell, neither the just nor the unjust may hope to avoid it, or need worry themselves by expecting it. It had selected the Adams family for its scaldings; no question.

The glue-works foreman, standing in the doorway of the brick shed, observed his employer’s eccentric approach, and doubtfully stroked a whiskered chin.

“Well, they ain’t no putticular use gettin’ so upset over it,” he said, as Adams came up. “When a thing happens, why, it happens, and that’s all there is to it. When a thing’s so, why, it’s so. All you can do about it is think if there’s anything you can do; and that’s what you better be doin’ with this case.”

Adams halted, and seemed to gape at him. “What—case?” he said, with difficulty. “Was it in the morning papers, too?”

“No, it ain’t in no morning papers. My land! It don’t need to be in no papers; look at the size of it!”

“The size of what?”

“Why, great God!” the foreman exclaimed. “He ain’t even seen it. Look! Look yonder!”

Adams stared vaguely at the man’s outstretched hand and pointing forefinger, then turned and saw a great sign upon the façade of the big factory building across the street. The letters were large enough to be read two blocks away.

“After the fifteenth of next month
this building will be occupied by
the J. A. Lamb Liquid Glue Co. Inc.”

A gray touring-car had just come to rest before the principal entrance of the building, and J. A. Lamb himself descended from it. He glanced over toward the humble rival of his projected great industry, saw his old clerk, and immediately walked across the street and the lot to speak to him.

“Well, Adams,” he said, in his husky, cheerful voice, “how’s your glue-works?”

Adams uttered an inarticulate sound, and lifted the hand that held his hat as if to make a protective gesture, but failed to carry it out; and his arm sank limp at his side. The foreman, however, seemed to feel that something ought to be said.

“Our glue-works, hell!” he remarked. “I guess we won’t have no glue-works over here not very long, if we got to compete with the sized thing you got over there!”

Lamb chuckled. “I kind of had some such notion,” he said. “You see, Virgil, I couldn’t exactly let you walk off with it like swallering a pat o’ butter, now, could I? It didn’t look exactly reasonable to expect me to let go like that, now, did it?”

Adams found a half-choked voice somewhere in his throat. “Do you—would you step into my office a minute, Mr. Lamb?”

“Why, certainly I’m willing to have a little talk with you,” the old gentleman said, as he followed his former employee indoors, and he added, “I feel a lot more like it than I did before I got that up, over yonder, Virgil!”

Adams threw open the door of the rough room he called his office, having as justification for this title little more than the fact that he had a telephone there and a deal table that served as a desk. “Just step into the office, please,” he said.

Lamb glanced at the desk, at the kitchen chair before it, at the telephone, and at the partition walls built of old boards, some covered with ancient paint and some merely weatherbeaten, the salvage of a house-wrecker; and he smiled broadly. “So these are your offices, are they?” he asked. “You expect to do quite a business here, I guess, don’t you, Virgil?”

Adams turned upon him a stricken and tortured face. “Have you seen Charley Lohr since last night, Mr. Lamb?”

“No; I haven’t seen Charley.”

“Well, I told him to tell you,” Adams began;—“I told him I’d pay you—”

“Pay me what you expect to make out o’ glue, you mean, Virgil?”

“No,” Adams said, swallowing. “I mean what my boy owes you. That’s what I told Charley to tell you. I told him to tell you I’d pay you every last—”

“Well, well!” the old gentleman interrupted, testily. “I don’t know anything about that.”

“I’m expecting to pay you,” Adams went on, swallowing again, painfully. “I was expecting to do it out of a loan I thought I could get on my glue-works.”

The old gentleman lifted his frosted eyebrows. “Oh, out o’ the glue-works? You expected to raise money on the glue-works, did you?”

At that, Adams’s agitation increased prodigiously. “How’d you think I expected to pay you?” he said. “Did you think I expected to get money on my own old bones?” He slapped himself harshly upon the chest and legs. “Do you think a bank’ll lend money on a man’s ribs and his broken-down old knee-bones? They won’t do it! You got to have some business prospects to show ’em, if you haven’t got any property nor securities; and what business prospects have I got now, with that sign of yours up over yonder? Why, you don’t need to make an ounce o’ glue; your sign’s fixed me without your doing another lick! That’s all you had to do; just put your sign up! You needn’t to—”

“Just let me tell you something, Virgil Adams,” the old man interrupted, harshly. “I got just one right important thing to tell you before we talk any further business; and that’s this: there’s some few men in this town made their money in off-colour ways, but there aren’t many; and those there are have had to be a darn sight slicker than you know how to be, or ever will know how to be! Yes, sir, and they none of them had the little gumption to try to make it out of a man that had the spirit not to let ’em, and the strength not to let ’em! I know what you thought. ‘Here,’ you said to yourself, ‘here’s this ole fool J. A. Lamb; he’s kind of worn out and in his second childhood like; I can put it over on him, without his ever—’ ”

“I did not!” Adams shouted. “A great deal you know about my feelings and all what I said to myself! There’s one thing I want to tell you, and that’s what I’m saying to myself now, and what my feelings are this minute!”

He struck the table a great blow with his thin fist, and shook the damaged knuckles in the air. “I just want to tell you, whatever I did feel, I don’t feel mean any more; not today, I don’t. There’s a meaner man in this world than I am, Mr. Lamb!”

“Oh, so you feel better about yourself today, do you, Virgil?”

“You bet I do! You worked till you got me where you want me; and I wouldn’t do that to another man, no matter what he did to me! I wouldn’t—”

“What you talkin’ about! How’ve I ‘got you where I want you’?”

“Ain’t it plain enough?” Adams cried. “You even got me where I can’t raise the money to pay back what my boy owes you! Do you suppose anybody’s fool enough to let me have a cent on this business after one look at what you got over there across the road?”

“No, I don’t.”

“No, you don’t,” Adams echoed, hoarsely. “What’s more, you knew my house was mortgaged, and my—”

“I did not,” Lamb interrupted, angrily. “What do I care about your house?”

“What’s the use your talking like that?” Adams cried. “You got me where I can’t even raise the money to pay what my boy owes the company, so’t I can’t show any reason to stop the prosecution and keep him out the penitentiary. That’s where you worked till you got me!”

“What!” Lamb shouted. “You accuse me of—”

“ ‘Accuse you’? What am I telling you? Do you think I got no eyes?” And Adams hammered the table again. “Why, you knew the boy was weak—”

“I did not!”

“Listen: you kept him there after you got mad at my leaving the way I did. You kept him there after you suspected him; and you had him watched; you let him go on; just waited to catch him and ruin him!”

“You’re crazy!” the old man bellowed. “I didn’t know there was anything against the boy till last night. You’re crazy, I say!”

Adams looked it. With his hair disordered over his haggard forehead and bloodshot eyes; with his bruised hands pounding the table and flying in a hundred wild and absurd gestures, while his feet shuffled constantly to preserve his balance upon staggering legs, he was the picture of a man with a mind gone to rags.

“Maybe I am crazy!” he cried, his voice breaking and quavering. “Maybe I am, but I wouldn’t stand there and taunt a man with it if I’d done to him what you’ve done to me! Just look at me: I worked all my life for you, and what I did when I quit never harmed you—it didn’t make two cents’ worth o’ difference in your life and it looked like it’d mean all the difference in the world to my family—and now look what you’ve done to me for it! I tell you, Mr. Lamb, there never was a man looked up to another man the way I looked up to you the whole o’ my life, but I don’t look up to you any more! You think you got a fine day of it now, riding up in your automobile to look at that sign—and then over here at my poor little works that you’ve ruined. But listen to me just this one last time!” The cracking voice broke into falsetto, and the gesticulating hands fluttered uncontrollably. “Just you listen!” he panted. “You think I did you a bad turn, and now you got me ruined for it, and you got my works ruined, and my family ruined; and if anybody’d ’a’ told me this time last year I’d ever say such a thing to you I’d called him a dang liar, but I do say it: I say you’ve acted toward me like—like a—a doggone mean—man!”

His voice, exhausted, like his body, was just able to do him this final service; then he sank, crumpled, into the chair by the table, his chin down hard upon his chest.

“I tell you, you’re crazy!” Lamb said again. “I never in the world—” But he checked himself, staring in sudden perplexity at his accuser. “Look here!” he said. “What’s the matter of you? Have you got another of those—?” He put his hand upon Adams’s shoulder, which jerked feebly under the touch.

The old man went to the door and called to the foreman.

“Here!” he said. “Run and tell my chauffeur to bring my car over here. Tell him to drive right up over the sidewalk and across the lot. Tell him to hurry!”

So, it happened, the great J. A. Lamb a second time brought his former clerk home, stricken and almost inanimate.

XXIV

About five o’clock that afternoon, the old gentleman came back to Adams’s house; and when Alice opened the door, he nodded, walked into the “living-room” without speaking; then stood frowning as if he hesitated to decide some perplexing question.

“Well, how is he now?” he asked, finally.

“The doctor was here again a little while ago; he thinks papa’s coming through it. He’s pretty sure he will.”

“Something like the way it was last spring?”

“Yes.”

“Not a bit of sense to it!” Lamb said, gruffly. “When he was getting well the other time the doctor told me it wasn’t a regular stroke, so to speak—this ‘cerebral effusion’ thing. Said there wasn’t any particular reason for your father to expect he’d ever have another attack, if he’d take a little care of himself. Said he could consider himself well as anybody else long as he did that.”

“Yes. But he didn’t do it!”

Lamb nodded, sighed aloud, and crossed the room to a chair. “I guess not,” he said, as he sat down. “Bustin’ his health up over his glue-works, I expect.”

“Yes.”

“I guess so; I guess so.” Then he looked up at her with a glimmer of anxiety in his eyes. “Has he came to yet?”

“Yes. He’s talked a little. His mind’s clear; he spoke to mama and me and to Miss Perry.” Alice laughed sadly. “We were lucky enough to get her back, but papa didn’t seem to think it was lucky. When he recognized her he said, ‘Oh, my goodness, ’tisn’t you, is it!’ ”

“Well, that’s a good sign, if he’s getting a little cross. Did he—did he happen to say anything—for instance, about me?”

This question, awkwardly delivered, had the effect of removing the girl’s pallor; rosy tints came quickly upon her cheeks. “He—yes, he did,” she said. “Naturally, he’s troubled about—about—” She stopped.

“About your brother, maybe?”

“Yes, about making up the—”

“Here, now,” Lamb said, uncomfortably, as she stopped again. “Listen, young lady; let’s don’t talk about that just yet. I want to ask you: you understand all about this glue business, I expect, don’t you?”

“I’m not sure. I only know—”

“Let me tell you,” he interrupted, impatiently. “I’ll tell you all about it in two words. The process belonged to me, and your father up and walked off with it; there’s no getting around that much, anyhow.”

“Isn’t there?” Alice stared at him. “I think you’re mistaken, Mr. Lamb. Didn’t papa improve it so that it virtually belonged to him?”

There was a spark in the old blue eyes at this. “What?” he cried. “Is that the way he got around it? Why, in all my life I never heard of such a—” But he left the sentence unfinished; the testiness went out of his husky voice and the anger out of his eyes. “Well, I expect maybe that was the way of it,” he said. “Anyhow, it’s right for you to stand up for your father; and if you think he had a right to it—”

“But he did!” she cried.

“I expect so,” the old man returned, pacifically. “I expect so, probably. Anyhow, it’s a question that’s neither here nor there, right now. What I was thinking of saying—well, did your father happen to let out that he and I had words this morning?”

“No.”

“Well, we did.” He sighed and shook his head. “Your father—well, he used some pretty hard expressions toward me, young lady. They weren’t so, I’m glad to say, but he used ’em to me, and the worst of it was he believed ’em. Well, I been thinking it over, and I thought I’d just have a kind of little talk with you to set matters straight, so to speak.”

“Yes, Mr. Lamb.”

“For instance,” he said, “it’s like this. Now, I hope you won’t think I mean any indelicacy, but you take your brother’s case, since we got to mention it, why, your father had the whole thing worked out in his mind about as wrong as anybody ever got anything. If I’d acted the way your father thought I did about that, why, somebody just ought to take me out and shoot me! Do you know what that man thought?”

“I’m not sure.”

He frowned at her, and asked, “Well, what do you think about it?”

“I don’t know,” she said. “I don’t believe I think anything at all about anything to-day.”

“Well, well,” he returned; “I expect not; I expect not. You kind of look to me as if you ought to be in bed yourself, young lady.”

“Oh, no.”

“I guess you mean ‘Oh, yes’; and I won’t keep you long, but there’s something we got to get fixed up, and I’d rather talk to you than I would to your mother, because you’re a smart girl and always friendly; and I want to be sure I’m understood. Now, listen.”

“I will,” Alice promised, smiling faintly.

“I never even hardly noticed your brother was still working for me,” he explained, earnestly. “I never thought anything about it. My sons sort of tried to tease me about the way your father—about his taking up this glue business, so to speak—and one day Albert, Junior, asked me if I felt all right about your brother’s staying there after that, and I told him—well, I just asked him to shut up. If the boy wanted to stay there, I didn’t consider it my business to send him away on account of any feeling I had toward his father; not as long as he did his work right—and the report showed he did. Well, as it happens, it looks now as if he stayed because he had to; he couldn’t quit because he’d ’a’ been found out if he did. Well, he’d been covering up his shortage for a considerable time—and do you know what your father practically charged me with about that?”

“No, Mr. Lamb.”

In his resentment, the old gentleman’s ruddy face became ruddier and his husky voice huskier. “Thinks I kept the boy there because I suspected him! Thinks I did it to get even with him! Do I look to you like a man that’d do such a thing?”

“No,” she said, gently. “I don’t think you would.”

“No!” he exclaimed. “Nor he wouldn’t think so if he was himself; he’s known me too long. But he must been sort of brooding over this whole business—I mean before Walter’s trouble he must been taking it to heart pretty hard for some time back. He thought I didn’t think much of him any more—and I expect he maybe wondered some what I was going to do—and there’s nothing worse’n that state of mind to make a man suspicious of all kinds of meanness. Well, he practically stood up there and accused me to my face of fixing things so’t he couldn’t ever raise the money to settle for Walter and ask us not to prosecute. That’s the state of mind your father’s brooding got him into, young lady—charging me with a trick like that!”

“I’m sorry,” she said. “I know you’d never—”

The old man slapped his sturdy knee, angrily. “Why, that dang fool of a Virgil Adams!” he exclaimed. “He wouldn’t even give me a chance to talk; and he got me so mad I couldn’t hardly talk, anyway! He might ’a’ known from the first I wasn’t going to let him walk in and beat me out of my own—that is, he might ’a’ known I wouldn’t let him get ahead of me in a business matter—not with my boys twitting me about it every few minutes! But to talk to me the way he did this morning—well, he was out of his head; that’s all! Now, wait just a minute,” he interposed, as she seemed about to speak. “In the first place, we aren’t going to push this case against your brother. I believe in the law, all right, and business men got to protect themselves; but in a case like this, where restitution’s made by the family, why, I expect it’s just as well sometimes to use a little influence and let matters drop. Of course your brother’ll have to keep out o’ this state; that’s all.”

“But—you said—” she faltered.

“Yes. What’d I say?”

“You said, ‘where restitution’s made by the family.’ That’s what seemed to trouble papa so terribly, because—because restitution couldn’t—”

“Why, yes, it could. That’s what I’m here to talk to you about.”

“I don’t see—”

“I’m going to tell you, ain’t I?” he said, gruffly. “Just hold your horses a minute, please.” He coughed, rose from his chair, walked up and down the room, then halted before her. “It’s like this,” he said. “After I brought your father home, this morning, there was one of the things he told me, when he was going for me, over yonder—it kind of stuck in my craw. It was something about all this glue controversy not meaning anything to me in particular, and meaning a whole heap to him and his family. Well, he was wrong about that two ways. The first one was, it did mean a good deal to me to have him go back on me after so many years. I don’t need to say any more about it, except just to tell you it meant quite a little more to me than you’d think, maybe. The other way he was wrong is, that how much a thing means to one man and how little it means to another ain’t the right way to look at a business matter.”

“I suppose it isn’t, Mr. Lamb.”

“No,” he said. “It isn’t. It’s not the right way to look at anything. Yes, and your father knows it as well as I do, when he’s in his right mind; and I expect that’s one of the reasons he got so mad at me—but anyhow, I couldn’t help thinking about how much all this thing had maybe meant to him;—as I say, it kind of stuck in my craw. I want you to tell him something from me, and I want you to go and tell him right off, if he’s able and willing to listen. You tell him I got kind of a notion he was pushed into this thing by circumstances, and tell him I’ve lived long enough to know that circumstances can beat the best of us—you tell him I said ‘the best of us.’ Tell him I haven’t got a bit of feeling against him—not any more—and tell him I came here to ask him not to have any against me.”

“Yes, Mr. Lamb.”

“Tell him I said—” The old man paused abruptly and Alice was surprised, in a dull and tired way, when she saw that his lips had begun to twitch and his eyelids to blink; but he recovered himself almost at once, and continued: “I want him to remember, ‘Forgive us our transgressions, as we forgive those that transgress against us’; and if he and I been transgressing against each other, why, tell him I think it’s time we quit such foolishness!”

He coughed again, smiled heartily upon her, and walked toward the door; then turned back to her with an exclamation: “Well, if I ain’t an old fool!”

“What is it?” she asked.

“Why, I forgot what we were just talking about! Your father wants to settle for Walter’s deficit. Tell him we’ll be glad to accept it; but of course we don’t expect him to clean the matter up until he’s able to talk business again.”

Alice stared at him blankly enough for him to perceive that further explanations were necessary. “It’s like this,” he said. “You see, if your father decided to keep his works going over yonder, I don’t say but he might give us some little competition for a time, ’specially as he’s got the start on us and about ready for the market. Then I was figuring we could use his plant—it’s small, but it’d be to our benefit to have the use of it—and he’s got a lease on that big lot; it may come in handy for us if we want to expand some. Well, I’d prefer to make a deal with him as quietly as possible—no good in every Tom, Dick and Harry hearing about things like this—but I figured he could sell out to me for a little something more’n enough to cover the mortgage he put on this house, and Walter’s deficit, too—that don’t amount to much in dollars and cents. The way I figure it, I could offer him about ninety-three hundred dollars as a total—or say ninety-three hundred and fifty—and if he feels like accepting, why, I’ll send a confidential man up here with the papers soon’s your father’s able to look ’em over. You tell him, will you, and ask him if he sees his way to accepting that figure?”

“Yes,” Alice said; and now her own lips twitched, while her eyes filled so that she saw but a blurred image of the old man, who held out his hand in parting. “I’ll tell him. Thank you.”

He shook her hand hastily. “Well, let’s just keep it kind of quiet,” he said, at the door. “No good in every Tom, Dick and Harry knowing all what goes on in town! You telephone me when your papa’s ready to go over the papers—and call me up at my house to-night, will you? Let me hear how he’s feeling?”

“I will,” she said, and through her grateful tears gave him a smile almost radiant. “He’ll be better, Mr. Lamb. We all will.”